<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the solemnetie wherewith the Catholike princes K. Phillip the III. and Quene Margaret were receyued in the Inglish Colledge of Valladolid the 22. of August. 1600. VVritten in Spanish by Don Ant. Ortiz and translated by Frauncis Riuers and dedicated to the right honorable the Lord Chamberlayne.</title>
            <title>Relación de la venida de los reyes católicos al Colegio Inglés de Valladolid. English</title>
            <author>Ortiz, Antonio, fl. 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119506</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854713</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854713</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20150</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20150)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 968:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the solemnetie wherewith the Catholike princes K. Phillip the III. and Quene Margaret were receyued in the Inglish Colledge of Valladolid the 22. of August. 1600. VVritten in Spanish by Don Ant. Ortiz and translated by Frauncis Riuers and dedicated to the right honorable the Lord Chamberlayne.</title>
                  <title>Relación de la venida de los reyes católicos al Colegio Inglés de Valladolid. English</title>
                  <author>Ortiz, Antonio, fl. 1600.</author>
                  <author>Rivers, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>VVith licence [by A. Conincx],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at N. [i.e. Antwerp] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Francis Rivers, of: Ortiz, Antonio. Relación de la venida de los reyes católicos al Colegio Inglés de Valladolid.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philip --  III, --  King of Spain, 1578-1621 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Margarita, --  de Austria, Queen, consort of Philip III, King of Spain, 1584-1611 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20150:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20150:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20150:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20150:2"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE SOLEMNETIE WHEREWITH THE CATHOLIKE PRINCES K. PHILLIP THE III. AND Quene Margaret were receyued in the Ingliſh Colledge of Valladolid the 22. of Auguſt. 1600.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVritten in ſpaniſh by Don Ant. Ortiz and tranſlated by Frauncis Riuers and dedicated to the right honorable the Lord Chamberlayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at N. vvith Licence. Anno 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20150:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20150:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE LORD OF HVNSDEN. L. CHAMBERLAYN, AND OF HER M<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PRIVYE COVNCEL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT honorable, I was drawen with no little curioſety and deſire, to read this booke when it came to my hands in the Spaniſh tongue, therly to gather the trewe cauſes, why the Spaniards fauor ſo much our Ingliſh Catholique fugeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and what hartes they cary to their country, euen theſe which for Religion, leaue it, to lyue in Seminaries abrode. And for as much as the relacion of theſe ſolemnityes written by a ſtraunger, and publiſhed in printe, to be read by ſo many gratie perſons as had bene preſent, muſt nedes be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with all truthe and ſinceritie, It could not chooſe (giuing notice of many particular ſpeches and actions) but diſcouer vnto vs the ſecret affects, of both parts. And therfore hauing ſeene it with attention, I was drawen with no leſſe deſire to put it in Ingliſh, that it might be read by your honor and the reſt of my good lords of her M. Councel. For yf the good will of the King of Spaine and his people to our countrymen, and their correſpondence to him and his, be founded in theſe honorable reſpects of conformity in Religion on the one ſide, and of piety and gratitude on the other, as by this relation
<pb facs="tcp:20150:4"/>
may be gathered (far different from the ſurmiſes which by other wayes I haue heard) me thinke the aſſurance of good meaninge, and knowen continuance of good will in them that were wont to be our beſt frends, though of late prouoked to be our enemyes, ſhould encorage vs much to Peace, and to renew the old confederations which our forefathers with ſo great wiſdome procured ſo many ages, with ſo great benefit of the land, eſpecially with thoſe in whom yet (vnder the profeſſion of hoſtility and exerciſe of war, wee fynde far better harts and more true affection to our Country and Countrymen, (as in this occaſion may beſene) then in others, whom with great care and cost we labor (I feare in vayne) to make of old enemyes, new frends. And this I beſeeke your honor to conſider, and to be a meane that it may come to her M. Knowlege. And ſo I take my leaue from Paris the 2. of December. 1600.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. euer at commaunde Frauncis Riuers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20150:4"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF THE SOLEMNITIE VVHEREVVITH THE PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENT AND CATHOLIKE PRINCES KINGE PHILIPPE the third and Queene Margaret weare receiued in the Engliſh Colledge of Valladolid the 22 of Auguſt. 1600.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Authors Epiſtle dedicatorie to the moſt gracious Lady Eliſabeth Clara Eugenia, Infanta of Spayne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING vndertaken at the requeſt of the Engliſh Colledge of this Citty and of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers theire benefactors and frendes, to write this Relation, of the Intertaynment &amp; good ſucceſſe of theire Mageſties coming to this Colledge wherat I was preſent: the ſame beeing to the great comfort of theſe baniſhed Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the ſame nation, and of many other graue and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonages of this kingdome, who for the great affection and good wil they beare to this Colledge, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue particular notice of all that paſſed: I thought my labour herein ſhould be the more approued and the Relation more gratefull to all ſortes of people, both here and in England, if it paſſed firſt through your highnes handes, aſwell for the naturall affection which this Kingdome beareth you, as alſo for the ſingular loue your highnes in many ocaſions hath ſhewed in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt to the Catholikes of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which no doubte
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20150:5"/>
by this late vicinetie and neighbourhood is much aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, whereof this Relation ſhal be to them a newe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and teſtimonie, and ſo I truſte of your highnes cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mencie, that you will vouchſafe to make them partakers of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, in confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whereof I haue entered into many party cularities and taken ocaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake of diuers circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces which wil not be tedious to your highnes, nor to the diſcreete reader with this reſpecte. And al though I could haue deſired more tyme &amp; comoditie for the writinge of any thinge that ſhould be preſented to your highnes, yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that the grace and orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this kinde of narration is the noueltie and freſhnes it bringes, I haue rather choſen to packe it vp in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, as my other buſineſſes and obligations did permitte, then to delaye it any longer, hoping that amongſte the fauours which your highnes hath ſhewed and doth dayly ſhewe to theſe Seminaries one ſhal be and not the leaſt, to accepte the good will and intention of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and not looke vpon the errors of the ſtile or other faultes that may be comitted.</p>
            <p>This whole Cittie is greatly comforted with the good newes that comes dayly of the diſcreet and Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> zeale &amp; valour which your highnes ſheweth in all occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſo doth erneſtly beſeech our Sauiour (who giueth you them) that he will defende and proſper your highnes for many happie yeares, &amp; the Arch duke in like manner, for the good of Chriſtendome, to whome I ſuppoſe this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation wil not be vngratefull. So wiſhing your highneſſes all fortunate ſucceſſe I humbly take my leaue from the Engliſh Colledge in Valladolid the 15. of Septemb. 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20150:5"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF THE COMMING OF THE CATHOLIKE PRINCES KING PHILIPPE THE THIRD AND QVEENE Margaret to the Engliſh Colledge of Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid, and of there receiuing theire the 22. of Auguſt. 1600.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, Infante of Spayne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>ING Philippe the third, Brother to your highnes, and Queene Margaret his wyf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered this famous Citie of Valliadolid vpon S. Margarets euen, the 19. of Iulij a day of great ioy and ſolemnitie, and of no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte to all this Citie, as it is like your highnes hath bene informed, and for that the weather was then very hotte in the Canicular dayes, and his Mageſties Palace in the fartheſt parte of the Citie, a greate way from the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Colledge, they deferred to deſire theire Mageſties to fauoure this theire Colledge with theire Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, for having receiued the like honour of his Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and of your highnes eight yeares agoe with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, vpon the inuention of the holly Protomartyre S. Stephen, which day is yet freſh in memorie in this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: it ſeamed they had the vvay open to expect and receiue this newe fauour of his Mageſtie.</p>
            <p>At this very tyme there came a good number of ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Colledge of S. Omers, of thoſe your highnes
<pb facs="tcp:20150:6"/>
Eſtates, erected by the King his Mageſtie that now is, eight yeares ſince (not without the ſpeciall prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God) wherein the Catholike children of Englad might be brought vp and inſtructed in vertue from theire te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der yeares, and learne the Latine tongue, Poetrie and Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, and from thence be ſent to the Seminaries of Spay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other more protounde ſciences as your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doth knowe. Among theſe ſtudientes there came ſome to yonge in yeares, that it ſemed they could ſcarſe ſpeake latine, but being examined they weare fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to be good Poetes and Rhetoricians, and two of the yongeſt were appointed to do obeyſance and giue to theire Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſties humble tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes in the name of theire Colledge: &amp; ſo with ſix others of theire company were conducted to the Pallace by their ſuperior and preſently admitted to audience, where hauing made the reuerence accuſtomed, one of them of fourteene yeares of age with good grace and modeſt countenance offered to ſpeake: But for that he was ſo younge &amp; ſo lately ariued, and that it might be feared leaſt with the preſence and Mageſtie of ſo great a kinge, he might be diſmayed and driuen out of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, the father thought good to preuent his Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and ſo told him the youth had a worde or two to ſpeake in the behalfe of his Colledge, but he feared his baſhfulnes &amp; that his harte would not ſerue him to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in preſence of his Mageſtie. The Kinge ſmiled and willed him with ſuch courteſie to ſpeake, that the childe tooke courage, and deliuered his Oration with ſo good a grace, ſo chearefully with ſo modeſt and decent action and ſo good pronuntiation and voice that he was well vnderſtoode, and his ſpeache very gratefull to his Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and to all that weare preſent who much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the liuelines and good courage of the childe, and for that his Oration was liked and commended of diuers graue and learned perſonnages that heard it, I ſuppoſe it wil be gratefull to your highnes that I ſette it downe in this place.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20150:6"/>
            <head>THE FIRST ORATION MADE TO THE KINGE, IN HIS PALLACE AT VALLADOLID, BY ONE OF THE STVDENTES OF THE EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Seminarie, of fourteen yeares of age, in which he giueth him thankes for the fauours done to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in S. Omers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ratis &amp; generoſis animis natura hoc dedit (Rex Catholice &amp; maxime) vt cum à quo beneficijs affecti ſunt, abſentem videre vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiſsime cupiant, &amp; praeſentem non ſine ſumma voluptate &amp; gaudio intueantur. Nos enim ex Audomarenſi Seminario (clariſsimo regiae liberalitatis tuae monumento) in Hiſpaniam acciti, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diernam laetitiam in pectoribus nostris geſtientem expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care ſatis non poſſumus, quam ex maiestatis vestrae iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiſsimo conſpectu haurimus, cum liceat pectus illud regium ſedem &amp; fontem beneficentiae intueri, &amp; oſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari illam inuictam dextram, cuius munificentiam libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitatem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> prius penè ſumus experti, quam huius lucis vſuram. Quod ſi flumina ſubterraneis receſsibus (naturae impetu) feruntur in mare, ex quo originem hauſerunt;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20150:7"/>
nos quam alacres quam laetos recurrere oportebit ad Maieſtatem veſtram (immenſum benefice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae Oceanum) ex quo haec quam ſpiramus vitae manauit, hic ſanguis que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliquando pro Chriſto fundendum ſperamus, effluxit.</p>
            <p>Cyrus Perſarum Rex, cum Lyſandrum Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium deduxiſſet in hortum, &amp; ille copiam, pulchritudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ordinem conſitarum arborum admiraretur; tunc glorians Cyrus, has (inquit) omnes mea manuplantaui, cui Lyſander; o beatum Perſarum Regem, cuius etiam in ſerendis arboribus peritiae fortuna coniuncta est. Nos autem quanto verius &amp; quanto iustius, o te foelicem &amp; beatum orbis Monarcham, qui cum ſummo faſtigio &amp; imperio ſummam pietatem &amp; religionem miſcuiſti; qui non terrenas &amp; caducas, ſed diuinas &amp; aeternas arbores in illo tuo Andomarenſi horto ſeminasti; quae ſatis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarant quanta prouidentia conſilio<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, a ſapientiſsima Maiestate vestra ſint conſitae, cum nouis quotidie in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina &amp; pietate progreſsibus ad martyrium vegite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. Specta oculis hos ſocios meos, &amp; in illis animo intuere (maxime &amp; potentiſsime Cyre) centum &amp; amplius alios nobiles pueros qui Audomaropoli remanſerunt: hi nouelli fidei flores, virentia haec germina religionis ex tuis hortis prodierunt; hae tenerae pietatis plantae ex tuis Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs profectae ſunt; tui ſunt hi fructus, tuae arbores quas regiae manu &amp; liberalitate plantasti, magnificis ſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aluiſti, largis beneficiorum fontibus irrigasti.</p>
            <p>Alexander Magnus cum in amicos omnia liberaliſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè effunderet, interrogatus a quodam quid ſibi reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, ſpem (inquit) non prodigis the ſauros tuos, quos in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicos Anglorum filios magnificentiſsimè ſpargis, ſed his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20150:7"/>
beneficijs acquiris certiſsimam ſpem conſequendi maiora. Alis enim in his pueris ſpem Angliae, ſpem publicae pacis, ſpem religionis &amp; fidei recuperandae. Erimus vbicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> locorum teſtes, &amp; praecones tuarum laudum. Erimus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitatis tuae non muta &amp; mortua, ſed viua &amp; loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia monumenta. Erimus veluti canales, per quos traducti beneficiorum tuorum imbres obruent Angliam vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam. Illi tui hostes, hac tua liberalitate, nobiliſsima, chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſsima<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> &amp; ab omnibus ſaeculis inandita vincentur. Venient ad te colendum, non inuiti, ſed volentes; non ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis ſed beneſicijs ſuperati.</p>
            <p>Camillus clariſsimus Romanorum Imperator cum Faliſcos (populos Italiae) obſidione premeret, omneſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilium virorum filij in eius potestatem proditi fuiſſent, nihil in pueros atrox, aut hoſtile geſsit, ſed inſigni iustitiae &amp; clementiae exemplo illaeſos integroſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> remiſit ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes. O te (Philippe maximè) fortiſsimum &amp; clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimum Camillum, cuius poteſtati, nos, ſi non hoſtium tuorum liberos certè ex hoſiili regione proficiſcentes, cum perſecutio prodidiſſet, benigniſsime recipis, liberaliſsimè educas, &amp; imbutos pietate, auctos, ornatoſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> doctrinis, remittis ad miſeram patriam ſubleuandam: &amp; erit illa tam ferrea, tam ſaxea, vt tam noua &amp; inuſitata cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia non moueatur? Sane, ſi illa fuerit (quod non ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus) ingrata, tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuum nulla obliterabit obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uio, cuius dulciſsimam memoriam in teneris puerorum pectoribus beneficiorum immortalium litteris exarasti. Si Anglia in impietate ſcelere<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> (quod abſit) perstiterit, hic noſter ſanguis, quem profide (Deo volente) fundemus, tantae illorum ingratitudini apud ſummum indicem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20150:8"/>
ſupplicium, &amp; Regiae tuae munificentiae iustum &amp; ſempiternum praemium postulabit &amp; obtinebit.</p>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
               <head>The ſame in Engliſh.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Noble and gratefull mindes (moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and mightie King) haue this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination by nature, towards the perſon of whome they haue receiued great benefits, that they deſier erneſtly to ſee him if he be abſent, and receiue ſingular ioy &amp; gladnes with his preſence: wherefore I and others my bretheren being come to Spayne from the Engliſh Seminarie of S. Omer, (that famous monument of your Mageſties libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie) we cannot ſuffitiently expreſſe the ioy we haue conceiued with the ſight of your mageſtie, nor the exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding comfort we feele being admitted to behould that princely and Royal breſt, the ſeate and fountaiue of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, and to kiſſe that inuincible right hand of muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence which we haue tried almoſt before we could breathe. And if the waters, caried by theire owne naturall force and inclination, finde paſſage thorow the earth by ſecret conductes and vaynes to the ſea, from whence they haue theire begining: how gladly and with what ioy &amp; deſire ſhould we recurre to your Mageſtie the fountayne and Ocean ſea of this great benefite, and bountie, out of which hath iſſued the ſpirituall life we liue, and whence we haue receued the bloude which we hope hereafter to ſhed for Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Cyrus King of Perſia hauing brought Lyſander the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonian into his garden, and he marueling much at the multitude, varietie, and order of the trees there plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Cyrus began to glorie, &amp; ſaid, all theſe I haue pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with myne owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to whom Lyſander anſwered, O happie king of the Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whoſe wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fortune ſo much
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20150:8"/>
fauoreth, that in the very planting of trees he hath proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſucceſſe. But with how much more truthe and reaſon may we ſay this of your Mageſtie (moſt happie Monarche of the world) who hath ioyned pietie with power, and ſo great zeale of Religion with ſo large Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of ſo many kingdomes, &amp; in fine (that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon may in all be like) hath ſet in this your garden of S. Omers, not earthly &amp; fading, but celeſtiall and eternal trees, which of them ſelues ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare, with what wiſdome and prouidence they were planted by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtie, ſeing they grow vp and floriſh dayly more and more in learning and vertu, and increaſe with incredible frute and deſire of Martyrdome. Behould then (moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtie and fortunate Cyrus) theſe my companions, and in them a hundered and more Noble and vertuous you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, which remaine yet at S. Omers: theſe younge and freſh flowers of faith, theſe greene buddes of vertue come out of your garden, theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der plantes of Religion haue ſprung vp in your Seminaries: theſe are the frutes, theſe the trees which your Mageſtie hath planted with your Royall and bountifull hand, which you haue nouriſhed with ſo great coſte, and watered with ſo abundant ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of pietie.</p>
               <p>Alexander the great, when he had freely beſtowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſte his frendes all he had, being aſked what he had kept for himſelf, anſwered, hope: So your Mageſtie dothe not loſe nor ſpend without purpoſe, that which ſo boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully you beſtowe vpon the catholike children of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for you nouriſhe in them, the hope of England; the hope of publike peace and quietnes; the hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; &amp; to recouer to Chriſt that countrie almoſt loſt. And in what place ſoeuer we ſhall come, we ſhal be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and heraldes of your praiſes; and not dumme and dead, but liuely and ſpeaking monuments of your libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie &amp; bountie; we ſhal be, as it were the vaines and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductes, by which the ſweete ſhowers of your benefites being deriued, ſhall ſtoppe the mouthes of your enemies
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20150:9"/>
and vainquiſh, them, not with armes, but with this moſt rare and chriſtian charitie, which you ſhewe to vs ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               <p>Camillus a Noble Emperour of the Romans, beſeiging the Phaliſcos a certaine people in Italie, and hauing in his handes all the noblemens ſonnes deliuered to him by treaſon, he ſuffered no rigor nor hoſtilitie to be vſed with them, but with notable demonſtration of iuſtice and clemencie ſent them back ſafe and without hurt, to their parentes.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo (O moſt mightie and courteous Prince) we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliuered to your Mageſties power and mercie by the rigour of the hereſie of England, your Mageſtie doth as another Camillus receius vs with the ſame cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, and bring vs vp with far greater benignetie &amp; loue, and in fine, after we are indued with pietie, &amp; ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorned with vertue and learning, you ſend vs backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againe to healp our miſerable countrie; &amp; is it then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that it can be ſo hard and ſtonie harted, as not to be moued with this extraordinarie and vnaccuſtomed cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie? Surely if our countrie could be ſo ingratefull, as we thinke it cannot, yet notwithſtanding no tyme nor forgetfullnes ſhal be able to extinguiſh this your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſties glorie, whoſe memorie and immortall benefites are ſo deepe grauen and rooted in the tender hartes of theſe children. If England ſhould ſtill perſiſte and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in hereſie (which God forbid) yet in that caſe this bloud of ours which we haue dedicated in teſtimonie of the catholike faith, will obtaine without doubt at the handes of the Allmightie, iuſt recompence and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting rewarde for this your Mageſties moſt chriſtian pietie and munificence.</p>
               <p>The Kinge was very much pleaſed with this Oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; willed the father to thanke the ſtudentes in his behalfe, and tolde him he had done wel to bring them to him, that he was glad he had ſeene them, and that with the next oportunitie he would ſee the reſt at home in theire
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20150:9"/>
Colledge, &amp; willed him to conduct them to the Quene. But for that ſhe was not then well at eaſe, the Oration which the ſecond had prouided for her Mageſtie was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred.</p>
               <p>Not long after the weather waxing more temperate, ſo as the king without inconuenience might come to the Colledge, for as much as it was erected by King Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippe the ſecond, father to your highnes, and therefore ſo peculiarly his owne and the kinges Mageſties that nowe is, as no communitie in this Citie is theirs with more particular obligation, it was thought conuenient that the Rector ſhould kiſſe his Mageſties hand, &amp; acquaint him with ſome particularities that might giue him occaſion of more comfort at his coming: &amp; ſo the 17. of Auguſt, after humble thankes for the ſpeciall fauours which in all occaſions he had ſhewed to this holy worke, he gaue him accompt of ſome thinges of no ſmall edification, and glorie of God, which had paſſed in ſpace of fower yeares and more that he had bene reſident in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and offering twice to break of his ſpeach, leaſt he might be tedious, both tymes the kinge willed him to goe forward, giuing ſignes of contentment with that which he tolde him, and in fine ſignified that ſhortly he would come to the Colledge, and cauſe warning to be giuen before his coming.</p>
               <p>A fewe dayes following, the Duke of Lerma ſent woord that theire Mageſties would be at the Colledge vpon S. Bernards day the 20. of Auguſt: and at the ſelf ſame ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the Ducheſſe of Lerma chiefe Chamberlaine to the Queene, ſent woord likewiſe that the other ſcholler, whoſe oration was deferred by reaſon of her Mageſties indiſpoſition, might now come and haue audieuce, and the next morning a coche was ſent from the Pallace, where in the younge Orator (with ſeuen others in his company) was carried, who both in ſtature and in yeares was leſſer then the former that ſpake to the kinge, although in his behauiour and deliuery of his ſpeech he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20150:10"/>
was nothing inferiour nor leſſe greatefull to the hearers. He acknowledged humble duty to her Mageſtie in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Colledge from whence he came, deſiring her protection and fauour: and for that this oration was to the ſame effect of the other aboue made to the king, though different in wordes and ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, I haue thought beſt (for breueties ſake) to omitt it.</p>
               <p>The Queene ſhewed herſelf very well contented with the Child and with that he had ſaid, and aſked many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities of the ſchollers there preſent, and of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of England, &amp; hauing had full relation of all, anſwered that ſhe was very glad to ſee theſe younge ones, and that before ſhe had much deſired to ſee them. And the father that conducted them replying that the king had inſinuated, howe the next day following he would be at the Colledge, and intreating likewiſe her Mageſtie to vouchſafe to doe them the ſame fauour, ſhe anſwered that in no caſe ſhe would fayle to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="preparation">
               <head>The preparation made to receiue theire Magiſties in the Engliſh Colledge.</head>
               <p>THe Church and both the Chappells were dreſſed with faire and riche orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. On the high Altar ſtood a newe tabernacle of carued worke, with three greate Images of the ſame, in the mideſt ſtoode S. Albane Patrone of this Colledge, and Protomarrir of England, on the right hand S. Thomas Archbyſhop of Canterbury, and on the left; the glorious Martyr S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond King of England that was ſhotte with arrowes to death; vnder theſe, ſtoode two faire and large caſkettes full of pretious Reliques of Martyrs, vpon the Altar was placed a notable relique of S. Albans fleſh ſett in golde and chriſtall, the foote wherof is a pretious ſtone of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te value, this Relique was giuen by King Philippe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to father Perſons for this Colledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20150:10"/>
The Church, was hanged about with hanginges wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were drawne the impriſonmentes and ordinary Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdomes of the Catholikes in England, ſett out in their coulors, and the pauement of the chauncel couered with turkie carpettes of curious worke, whereupon were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced twoe ſeates for theire Mageſties, couered with cloth of golde. I durſt not preſume to weary your highnes with the relation of theſe circumſtances, if your affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this holy worke, and the comfort that your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours the Engliſh Catholikes will receiue to vnderſtand theſe particularities, did not excuſe me.</p>
               <p>The firſt courte through which his Mageſtie was to enter into the Colledge was hanged all about with coſtly hanginges, and likewiſe all the reſt of the way which he was to paſſe, till he came to the great hall wher your highnes was once receiued. VVithin the foreſaid courte, at the entrance of a gate and broade paſſage new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, that leades to the inner roomes, was written in faire text hand in ſpaniſh. <hi>El para bicn de la venida a ſus Mageſtades</hi> (that is.) Theire Mageſties wellcome. And both ſides of the gate were coueted with verſes in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye languages to the ſame effect. The Latine verſes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I wil put downe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ianua pande fores, vt ſolis, quem colit orbis.</l>
                  <l>Auguſtum angusto limine lumen eat.</l>
                  <l>Sit domus iſta humilis, nec tanto digna Monarcha,</l>
                  <l>Nil ſpernit Pietas; ianua pande fores.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Here the Kinge ſtayed and turned him ſelf to the Queene, and ſmiling, ſayed, lo they bid thee wellcome, and ſo paſſed on to the great hall, where they were to be receiued which was more richly hung then the reſt, and in the middeſt, on the right ſide was placed a cloth of eſtate ſutable to the hanginges, with twoe embrodered chaires for theire Mageſties. Ouer the kings chaire hung
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20150:11"/>
his picture drawen all armed from the girdle vpward, with his Helmet by him, &amp; the <hi>Tuſon,</hi> about his necke, which is a chayne &amp; on it hanging the golden fleice: on his arme a ſheilde, and within it a lion; vpon his breaſt was written <hi>Signaculum ſuper cor tuum,</hi> &amp; vpon his ſheil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, <hi>Signaculum ſuper brachium tuum,</hi> and vnder his picture theſe Latine verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Manſuetum ſignat pectus mitiſsimus agnus,</l>
                  <l>Inuictum bello cincta leone manus.</l>
                  <l>Quondam fulgebant Agamemnonis arma leone,</l>
                  <l>Iaſon aurato vellere diues erat.</l>
                  <l>Vne Philippe geris vellus, fortcm<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leonem,</l>
                  <l>Qui mundo Iaſon qui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Agamemnon eris.</l>
                  <l>Clemens pace, potens armis, inuicte rebelli,</l>
                  <l>Mitis victo, animis agne, manu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leo.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Ouer the Queenes chaire hung likewiſe her picture in a robe of crimſen (which happened very well, &amp; gaue contentement to many for that ſhe came atyred in the very ſame colour) ſhe was pictured at the window of a Caſtell (made after the manner and forme of the Armes of Caſtillia) with a pomegranate in the one ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; in the other the goulden fleece, with theſe verſes vnder written.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Granatum ſignat foecundam, bellipotentem</l>
                  <l>Turris, in aurato vellere forma micat.</l>
                  <l>Praeſes erat turri Pallas, granata gerebat</l>
                  <l>Iuno tulit quondam vellera fulua Venus.</l>
                  <l>Iuno granatum Venus aurum arcem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Minerua</l>
                  <l>Deſerat, in<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vnam gloria trina cadat.</l>
                  <l>Pallas, Iuno, Venus, fortis foecunda decora,</l>
                  <l>Turrim Pomum aurum, Margaris vna tenes.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20150:11"/>
Betweene theſe two pictures were drawen the Kings armes, with a Metaphoricall applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theire proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and excellencies, according to euery ſeuerall coate, applied to theire Mageſties in the Manner following.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quadrupedum indomitos reges (Philippe) leones,</l>
                  <l>Penningerum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> duces Aquilas, Mauortia caſtra,</l>
                  <l>Arborum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> decus Granata, &amp; Lilia florum,</l>
                  <l>Et tanto auratum Vellus ſudore petitum,</l>
                  <l>Marte domas ſolus ſolus pietate reſeruas;</l>
                  <l>Aeternum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eadem quid ni quoque ſolus habebis,</l>
                  <l>Cùm tibi quae pellant vim vectes, quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuetur</l>
                  <l>Parta prius caeci famuletur numinis alea,</l>
                  <l>Quae vult Aeoirepetens ſua lumina Phoebus,</l>
                  <l>Cuncta tuis radijs caelo moderaris ab alto.</l>
                  <l>Ergo cum Granata tibi, cum Caſtra, Leones,</l>
                  <l>Alea, prepes auis, cum Vellus, Lilia, Vectes,</l>
                  <l>Dant ſua colla iugo veſtro, pacem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> repoſcant,</l>
                  <l>Iure tibi flores, tibi fructus, bella, volucres,</l>
                  <l>Quadrupedes, fortuna tibi, tibi parta per vndas</l>
                  <l>Praeda ſatis, quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> astra alto figuntur Olympo,</l>
                  <l>Qui terris Mars alter, &amp; alter in aethera Phoebus,</l>
                  <l>Nata creas radijs, ſpolia acri Marte reſeruas:</l>
                  <l>Sic tibi terra, Polus, Sors, Mauors, militat aether,</l>
                  <l>Et tua Neptunus pelago ſi cepta ſecundet,</l>
                  <l>Spargetur totum tandem tua fama per orbem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>On the left ſide of the cloth of eſtate was a place for the maydes of honour, and at the vper end of the hall hung a very liuely picture of the Martyr father Henrie VValpole ſomety me Miniſter of this Colledge, who fiue yeares agoe was cruelly put to death in England, he was pourtraied his whole ſtature, with his left hand vpon the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20150:12"/>
racke, wheron he had bene nine tymes tormented, with a rope about his necke, &amp; his breaſt opened with the knife wherewith he was emboweled, and in his right hand he held his hart, which he offered vp to Chriſt, with ſo liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and affectuous a countenance that it moued all to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion that beheld it. Vnder the picture were twoe ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chens with theſe ſpaniſh verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nueue vezes Valpolo atormentado</l>
                  <l>En eculeo, ſale victorioſo,</l>
                  <l>Por las publicas calles arraſtrado,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n vn palo le cuelgan afrentoſo,</l>
                  <l>Y el pecho abierto el coraçon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cado</l>
                  <l>Viuo le deſquartizan, y el gozoſo</l>
                  <l>Sufre carcel, cadenas, ſogasy grillos,</l>
                  <l>Eculeos, horcas, fuegos, y cuchillos.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seminario Anglicano al alto cielo</l>
                  <l>Da gracias, por auer de ti ſalido</l>
                  <l>Quien con ſu ſangre illuſtra el patrio ſuelo.</l>
                  <l>Y a ti dexa con ella ennoblecido,</l>
                  <l>Y muriendo en el campo del duelo</l>
                  <l>Al enemigo dexa en el vencido,</l>
                  <l>Ganando en tan inclita victoria</l>
                  <l>Fama en la tierra, y en el cielo gloria.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Vnder this picture was opened a great dore to the ſchooles of the Colledge, where the muſike ſtoode. On both ſides of the dore were ſeates couered with ſilke, and a ſett of violes, which the Earle of Fuenſaldan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſome yeares a goe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Colledge, with bookes of muſike, and betweene the twoe ſeates a payre of Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales of an excellent ſound, that Don Franciſco de Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſo Biſhop of Cordoua gaue to this Church to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the other inſtruments which the ſchollers vſe with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20150:12"/>
great dexteritie in the ſolemnities of Maſſe and Euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſong vpon feaſtiuall dayes, which they ſing with no leſſe deuotion and proprietie of Eccleſiaſticall ceremonies, as the Inſtitution and ſtatutes of theſe Seminaries ordayne.</p>
               <p>The hanginges of the afore ſaide hall were ſett rounde about with ingenious hietogliphickes &amp; verſes in Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Spaniſh &amp; other languages, whereof the one half were compoſed in prayſe of the king, &amp; the other of the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. In the ſame manner was dreſſed all the waye that the king was to paſſe from the Church to the great hall with Emblemes, Epigrammes, Elegies and Lyricke verſes, and amongſt the teſt was one famous Poeme wherein Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion aſked of God the armes wherewith the Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell S. Michaell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered the dragon, that with the ſame the king might alſo conquere him and baniſh him out of all his countries &amp; dominions. This Poeme for the arte and inuention wherewith it was compoſed, was much maruelled at, &amp; much deſired, but becauſe it was ſo long contayning aboue fowerhundred verſes it could not well be printed here. The reſt of the verſes, were of the kings coming to the Colledge, to giue him thankes for the fauours which both he and his father had ſhewed to this worke, and to ſignifie the ioye and comforte which the ſtudentes conceiued to ſee them ſelues in this theire ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſolitude, viſited and ſo much fauoured by ſo potent and Catholike Princes. Among theſe verſes there were but fewe in Spaniſh, becauſe the recollection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſchollers liue doth not ſuffer them to haue ſo much vſe of the language as is required for verſes, and becauſe this feaſt ſhould be onely theirs, as was intended by theire Mageſties, whoſe meaning was to be receiued and feaſted only by them. The Latine verſes were many in number and ſo full of varietie &amp; good inuention, that diuers perſons of the moſt learned of this vniuerſitie, were importunate to haue them all printed, but becauſe it is not meete to trouble your highnes with a volume, and on the other ſide, for as much as they were the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20150:13"/>
parte of the feaſt, and therefore are not wholy to be omitted, I haue choſen out ſome fewe of the ſhorteſt that by them your highnes may make iudgement of the reſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <head>Some of the verſes made in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Colledge of Valladolid to congratulate theire Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties comming.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Hierogliphicks vpon the kings armes.</head>
               <p>THere was drawen in colours a caſtell, and in it were lodged certaine Ingliſh ſtudents in their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legial habite, one had in his hand a Pomegranat with this poſie <hi>Paſtus,</hi> an other the goulden fleece with this poſie <hi>Vestis.</hi> A lyon (which is alſo parte of the armes) kept the caſtel gate, with this title; <hi>Custos,</hi> ouer the caſtel an eagle (which is an other coate) ſoringe in the ayre, caried one of the ſchollers, with this title, <hi>Dux in Caelum,</hi> and the whole picture was compaſſed about with this poſie, <hi>Philippus nobis omnia in omnibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Arx praebet tutam miſeris fugientibus aedem,</l>
                  <l>Dant granata cibos, aurea lana tegit.</l>
                  <l>Cuſtodit vigilat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leo, vehit ales ad aſtra</l>
                  <l>Quae phrygium puerum vexerat ante Ioui.</l>
                  <l>Diues hic eſt clipaeus, rerum the ſaurus abundans</l>
                  <l>Nil<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deeſt miſeros quod reuelare queat.</l>
                  <l>Arx recipit, vellus veſtit, granata<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> paſcunt,</l>
                  <l>Nos Leo cuſtodit, ducit ad aſtra Aquila.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20150:13"/>
Viue diu Princeps fortunatiſsimè nobis,</l>
                  <l>Arx, Vellus, granata, Leo, Iouis armiger ales,</l>
                  <l>Hoſpitium, veſtis, paſtus, vigil, author ad astra.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An other vpon the ſame armes.</head>
               <p>There was drawen an eagle in the aire, and the birdes doing her homage as to there Queene, next was a Lion on the earth whome the other beaſts acknowledged for there kinge, then after a ſhippe ſayling in the ſea which had in the ſterne, in the flagges, and ſayles, painted the golden fleece, and fiſhes gathered a bout it with thes verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ecce tibi Leo magnanimus, Regina volucrum,</l>
                  <l>Quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tulit Colcha vellus ab vrbe ratis.</l>
                  <l>Magnammum metuunt animalia cuncta Leonem,</l>
                  <l>Et volucres Aquilam, caecula turba ratem.</l>
                  <l>Ergo tibi parent volucres, animalia, piſces,</l>
                  <l>Omnia quae caelum, terra, ſalum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tenent.</l>
                  <l>Erige te Princeps, &amp; regna immenſa tuere,</l>
                  <l>Imperijs deſunt ſydera ſola tuis.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An other vpon the whole armes of Spaine which theſe verſes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haeres magnanimi patris, qui gentis Iberae</l>
                  <l>Sceptra per innumeros miſſa tueris Auos.</l>
                  <l>Quot titulos clipeo, tot iunge in pectore laudes,</l>
                  <l>Et noli a proauis degenerare tuis.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20150:14"/>
Religio turrim te ſentiat, atra Leonem</l>
                  <l>Haereſis, &amp; niueae Lilia pacis amae.</l>
                  <l>Lilia granatis coniunge ſalubribus, vt ſic</l>
                  <l>Aſpicias patriae creſcere gentis opes.</l>
                  <l>Imbuat vltrices infidus Perſa ſagittas,</l>
                  <l>Et cadat ante tuos Turcia victa pedes.</l>
                  <l>More Aquilae terras contemne, &amp; in aethera ſurge:</l>
                  <l>Sola decent pennas ſydera celſa tuas.</l>
                  <l>Arx iuſtis, Leo ſacrilegis, Flos candido Iberis,</l>
                  <l>Terror Turcarum, numinis ales aue.</l>
                  <l>Harum virtutum acceſſu tua gloria creſcet,</l>
                  <l>Vt ſilicum attritu feruida flamma micat.</l>
                  <l>Hae tibi ſydeream texent ſuper aſtra coronam,</l>
                  <l>Hae tibi &amp; in teris vellera fulua dabunt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The ſelf ſame armes were in an other place in their colours, with this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lilia, quidue Aquilae, Granatum, Caſtra, Leones,</l>
                  <l>Oſtendunt? quis ſit (clare Philippe) not ant.</l>
                  <l>Lilia ſpem, (ſperas dum ſpiras) candida ſignant</l>
                  <l>Quis decor internus exterior<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi.</l>
                  <l>Regia quid vaſtum ſcandens per inane volucris?</l>
                  <l>Quonam animus tend at (magne Philippe) not at.</l>
                  <l>Imperij regimen Granatuui iura<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> monſtrat,</l>
                  <l>Incluſos caſtrum nos tua dextra tegit.</l>
                  <l>Quid vigilans fortiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Leo? tua robora ſentit</l>
                  <l>Hostis, &amp; excubias ſedula cura not at.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20150:14"/>
               <head>Vpon the armes of the Kingdome of Caſtile.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>There were painted the armes of Caſtile alone, with ſome Engliſh ſchollers in the caſtels, and ouer them this poſie</hi> hic hoſpitamur, <hi>and ouer the lions,</hi> hic defendimur.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hoſpitium nobis tua ſunt caſtella Philippe,</l>
                  <l>His valet Angliaco viuere pulſus agro.</l>
                  <l>Tutus erit quem caſtra tegent: ni ſufficit vnus,</l>
                  <l>Arcebit cunctas rex leo ab arceferas.</l>
                  <l>Ergo veni, Britanne veni, tibi tecta Philippus</l>
                  <l>Caſtellae tribuet castra, teget<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leo.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An other vpon the ſame armes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>There was painted a caſtel of the armes of Caſtile, and vpon one of the pinacles a lion watching; and vpon an other was the golden fleece: and in the middeſt an eagle flying vp to the clouds out of which came thunder and lightning, with this poſie.</hi> Turris inexpugnabilis, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita vigilantia, audacia, opibus.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nec timor aut error turtim nec perdet egeſtas,</l>
                  <l>Aurea quam ſeruat lana, leo, ac aquila.</l>
                  <l>Nam quid deeſſe poteſt turri cui pendeat aurum?</l>
                  <l>Cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leo vigilat, prodier arte nequit.</l>
                  <l>Et quis terrebit panſis quem protegit alis,</l>
                  <l>Quae ventos, imbres, flumina temnit auis?</l>
                  <l>O foelix turris vigili munit a leone,</l>
                  <l>Audaci<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aquila, vellere diues aue,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20150:15"/>
               <head>An other of the ſame.</head>
               <p>There was painted a pomegranat tree, and vnder it, one dying his clothes wich the flowers: and an other eating the fruite: an other ſleeping vnder the ſhade: an other chaſing away ſerpentes with the bowes as with weapons: an other curing the inflammation of his eyes with the leaues: and about the tree this poſie <hi>Salus: quies.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flos</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">1.</seg>, <hi>fructus</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">2.</seg>, <hi>radix</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">3.</seg>, <hi>ramus</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">4.</seg>, <hi>folium<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                     <seg rend="above">5.</seg> 
                     <hi>Philippus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Granati, ornatus</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">1.</seg>, <hi>pastus</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">2.</seg>, <hi>ſopar</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">3.</seg>, <hi>arma</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">4.</seg>, <hi>medela</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">5.</seg>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nudis</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">1.</seg>, <hi>ieiunis</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">2.</seg>, <hi>feſsis</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">3.</seg>, <hi>pugnantihus</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">4.</seg>, <hi>aegris</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">5.</seg>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flore</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">1.</seg> 
                     <hi>ornat, fructu</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">2.</seg> 
                     <hi>paſcit, radice</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">3.</seg> 
                     <hi>ſoporat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ramo</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">4.</seg> 
                     <hi>armat, folia</hi>
                     <seg rend="above">5.</seg> 
                     <hi>ſanat, cuncta omnibus vnus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>In another place was painted a great laurel tree, &amp; a crowne of the ſame laurel with this poſie <hi>ſemper vire<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> On the one ſide were certaine cloudes with deſcription of thunder and lightning, and ſome Ingliſh ſcholers which ſhrowded them ſelues vnder the tree, &amp; about them was written, <hi>ſecura.</hi> On the other ſide were ſwarmes of waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, which ſtung others, and they gathered the bowes to heale the ſtinging with this ſubſcription <hi>ſalubris.</hi> Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the tree were many bookes which with the laurel leaues weare preſerued from mothes, with this inſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>tinea non comedet eos.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ite ſub Hiſpana iuuenes requieſcite lauro,</l>
                  <l>Anglia quos diro fulmine ſaeua premit.</l>
                  <l>Ite, ſalutifera ſanentur vulner a fronde,</l>
                  <l>Vulnera quae miſeris impia veſpa facit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20150:15"/>
Diuinóſque libros haec laurus ſacra coronet,</l>
                  <l>Et tactum nullo verme volumen erit.</l>
                  <l>Ergo Phoebaea lauro te cinge Philippe,</l>
                  <l>Iustius in titulos conuenit illa tuos.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>There was painted the Sunne, and the Moone looſing her light with the Sunne ſhine: &amp; a bordet of roſes, which with the ſame Sunne beames did grow &amp; floriſh.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haereticus luna eſt formas variandus in omnes,</l>
                  <l>Martyr purpureo tincta cruore roſa.</l>
                  <l>Lumine ſic perit haereticus lunaticus isto,</l>
                  <l>Hoc vitam roſeus lumine martyr habet.</l>
                  <l>Viue diu fulgens, vt condas lumine lunas,</l>
                  <l>Et vegetes multas (maxime Phoebe) roſas.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Alia eiuſdem interpretatio.</head>
                  <l>Luna regit Turcas, roſáque eſt inſigne Britannis:</l>
                  <l>Illos lucendo, hos non radiando premis.</l>
                  <l>Pande ſacros radios, non fulget Turcica luna:</l>
                  <l>Subtrahe, et Angliacae iam periêre roſae.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>There was drawen a piller and vpon it a globe of the earth, with theſe verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dum pater humanas moriendo linqueret oras,</l>
                  <l>Qui terrae ferres pondera, ſolus eras.</l>
                  <l>Herculea Athlantis ſuppleuit munera ceruix,</l>
                  <l>Qui caeli ferret pondera, ſolus erat.</l>
                  <l>Si perit Alcides, rurſus geſtabit olympum</l>
                  <l>Atlas, vel nullus grande leuabit onus.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20150:16"/>
Si moreris, terram valido qui robore portet,</l>
                  <l>Ni genitor redeat, non erit vllus Atlas.</l>
                  <l>Pondera fer validis princeps librata lacertis,</l>
                  <l>Astra tuis humeris non graue pondus erunt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>There was painted a lion roring and other beaſts fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon the earth for feare of his voice, with this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. <hi>Leo rugit, quis non timebit?</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quid facies leo bellipotens? elapſa minaces</l>
                  <l>Fauces, in campis libera praeda fugit.</l>
                  <l>Vox tua rugitu diuinas perſonet aures</l>
                  <l>Emiſſáſque pio pectore funde preces.</l>
                  <l>Rugitu hoc, hoſtes, vires animoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relinquent,</l>
                  <l>Et cadat ante tuos territa praeda pedes:</l>
                  <l>Sic Sampſon, Dauid<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> olim vicêre, quod armis</l>
                  <l>Nunquam feciſſent, hoc potuere prece.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>There was painted a rock, and vpon it pomegranats, which being preſſed gaue out there iuice, with this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. <hi>Dabo tibi muſtum malorum granatorum meorum.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Martyribus ſanctum quem poſsint inde eruorem,</l>
                  <l>Fundere, granatis (magne Philippe) foues.</l>
                  <l>Nam quae torcular torquet granata Britannum,</l>
                  <l>Sunt tua quae poenis gens inimic a premit.</l>
                  <l>Granatis expreſſa fluunt ſuauiſsima muſta,</l>
                  <l>Sic magno praebes dulcia vina Deo.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>There was painted two dragons flieng from a lion, which purſued them with theſe verſes vnder written.</head>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20150:16"/>
                  <l>Maius ſi Herculeis onus lacertis,</l>
                  <l>Hoſtes vincere praelio gemellos,</l>
                  <l>Maior Thebigina es Philippe maior,</l>
                  <l>Rex vincis, aquila vt duos dracones,</l>
                  <l>Bis binos poteras domare ſolus.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Alia eiuſdem explicatio.</head>
                  <l>Peſtiferi fugiunt aquila veniente dracones,</l>
                  <l>Hostivus intent at praelia dira ſuis.</l>
                  <l>Sic fugat haereticos generoſo corde Philippus,</l>
                  <l>Seruat mundum aquila haec, haereſis hydranecat.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>
                  <hi>There was deſcribed a mountaine with a freſh and plaiſant medow, wherin was feeding a flock of lambes, the mountaine was compaſſed about with the chaine of the golden fleece of Spaine this chayne reſembleth flintſtones which ſtriking vpon the ſteele caſt out flames of fire, wich this poſie</hi> tua custodia:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ne fera per medias crudelis funera caulas</l>
                  <l>Edat, &amp; innocuas vulnere perdat oues,</l>
                  <l>Pinguia flammiuomis ſinguntur paſcua ſaxis,</l>
                  <l>Nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fer as abigit quae micat ignis ſilex.</l>
                  <l>Quaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> canum vigilans neque at depellere cura,</l>
                  <l>Rauca<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> paſtorum murmura, flamma fugat.</l>
                  <l>Flamma fugat, lapidéſque fugant, his cingere ceptis</l>
                  <l>Si rabidos morſus ſallere preda cupis.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the Catholike Princes protectors of the Engliſh Seminaries.</head>
               <p>There was painted a ſhip toſſed with a furisus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and kept faſt with two anchers.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20150:17"/>
                  <l>Anchora ſpes nautis, fragilis ſpes anchora cymbae:</l>
                  <l>Haec fultus, tumidas nauita temnit aquas.</l>
                  <l>Quos metues fluctus Anglorum cymba minaces?</l>
                  <l>Anchora dat firmam ſpem, geminata tibi.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A Hierogliphicke of the Ingliſh Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries in Spaine.</head>
               <p>There was painted the Arke of Noe, &amp; in it the Ingliſh ſtudents with theſe verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Noëmo arca fuit ſalus, ſuiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Natis, dum valido Deus feracem</l>
                  <l>Terram mergeret imbre mergit atrox</l>
                  <l>Fluctus haereſeon ſolum Britannum,</l>
                  <l>Arcam quaerimus; eſt &amp; arca nobis</l>
                  <l>Littus Heſperium, ſalus Britanno,</l>
                  <l>Foelix quod ſoueat, itaiste foelix</l>
                  <l>Taline pereat protectus arca,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An other of the citie of Valladolid.</head>
               <p>There were painted certaine ſtagges carying fire vpon their hornes taken from the armes of this citie of Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid, and with the ſame they ſet on fire heapes of cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, vnderwhich were gathered todes, ſerpentes, battes, and owles, all which with the light and fire fled a way, with theſe verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cynnama diuinae pietatis rapta Britannis</l>
                  <l>Nicticolae volucres, hydráque ſaeua premit.</l>
                  <l>Ite domum celeres, quorum ardua cornua, cerui,</l>
                  <l>Armat odorifera Pincia ſancta face.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20150:17"/>
Diffugite ô angues, ſtygij properate colubri,</l>
                  <l>Ecce ferunt ſacros cornua odora focos.</l>
                  <l>Vos quoque lucifuge procul hinc proculite volucres,</l>
                  <l>Lux vbi diſcuſſa fulgida nocte micat.</l>
                  <l>Sed tu laeta veni depulſis Anglia monstris.</l>
                  <l>Et fidei antiquae Cynnama ſancta cape.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An other of the ſame.</head>
               <p>There was painted the ſame armes of valladolid, and ouer againſt them the armes of Ingland, which are three lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, flying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fire: with this poſie, <hi>fugie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a facie ignis.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Perdomat idomitos effraenatoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> leones</l>
                  <l>Flamma ferus vincit, vincitur igne leo.</l>
                  <l>Angliaci ſaeuo lanient ne dente leones</l>
                  <l>Innocuas pecudes, innocuoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> greges.</l>
                  <l>Ferte citi Heſperias Britanna ad littora flammas,</l>
                  <l>Indomitaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> feras Pincia flamma domet.</l>
                  <l>Sic fugient timidi poſita feritate leones,</l>
                  <l>Sic poterit tutum viuere mite pecus.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>And other of the Ingliſh Seminaries.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>There were painted three youthes clothed with the barcke of trees, and certaine birds called, ſtimphalides, hauing there bils faſtened in the ſame barcke, wherin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nig caught they dyed, with this poſie:</hi> triumphus pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gignit auem tellus Arabum, Stymphalida dicunt,</l>
                  <l>Aenea quae penetrat morſibus arma feris.</l>
                  <l>Sed tamen arboreo munitum cortice corpus</l>
                  <l>Perdere cum tentat, cortice fixa perit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20150:18"/>
Cernite quam ſaeuas ſtymphalidas Anglia gignit,</l>
                  <l>Vt Christi lacerat ſoeda volucris oues.</l>
                  <l>O vos quos validis patientia viribus armat,</l>
                  <l>Cortice quos fidei Pincia ſilua tegit.</l>
                  <l>Porgite opem, ſi ſaeua petat vos haerefis vngue,</l>
                  <l>Si latus innocuum foeda cruentat auis:</l>
                  <l>Vulnera dum infigit ſe ſacro in cortice figet,</l>
                  <l>Et capta haerebit morſibus ipſa ſuis.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>There was painted a nightingal ſinging in a tree and a ſerpent deceitfully creeping op to catch her.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quam fouit ſacris Philomelam Pincia ſiluis</l>
                  <l>Et docuit dulces ore ciêre ſonos</l>
                  <l>Dum canit Angligenis tectis illabitur anguis,</l>
                  <l>Et rapit innocuam, dum pia verba mouet.</l>
                  <l>Non perit, aut canere omittet, ſed ſcandet Olympum,</l>
                  <l>Et canet aeternos ſuauiùs illa modos.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>
                  <hi>There was painted a tree caled Lothos which groweth in Libra, whoſe leaues cloſe vp towards night, and in the morning when the Sunne beginneth to ſhine they open a gaine, ſhewing them ſelues very freſh and faire: theſe leaues were painted open looking towardes the Sunne riſing, with this poſie:</hi> O ſi perpetuo.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lothos in Libicis virens</l>
                  <l>Arbos humida partibus,</l>
                  <l>Solis tacta coloribus</l>
                  <l>Pandit fulgida Ramos.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20150:18"/>
                  <l>Grates reddit Apollini,</l>
                  <l>Cuius lumine ſplendido,</l>
                  <l>Frondes creſcere flexiles,</l>
                  <l>Fructus ſentit amenos:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Donec Heſperus vmbrifer</l>
                  <l>Noctem ſomniferam ferens,</l>
                  <l>Ramos contrahere arborem</l>
                  <l>Cogit, ſydere dempto:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lothi nos quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pandimus</l>
                  <l>Palmas inclyte Rex tibi,</l>
                  <l>Dignas iure<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> debitas</l>
                  <l>Grates, reddimus Angli.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Per te viuimus (inclyte)</l>
                  <l>Per te creſcimus in fide,</l>
                  <l>Virtutiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> laboribus</l>
                  <l>Florent germina veſtris:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Non noctis tenebrae graues</l>
                  <l>Nobis eripiant diem,</l>
                  <l>Nec te viuificum iubar</l>
                  <l>Rex lux maxima mundi.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>There was painted an eagle feeding certaine doues in her neſt, with this poſie. <hi>Pietas ſupra naturam.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mutauit natura vices, miracula cerno:</l>
                  <l>Et recipit leges terra beata nouas.</l>
                  <l>Regia pallantes volucris generoſa columbas</l>
                  <l>Proteget, in nido dat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> alimenta ſuo.</l>
                  <l>Tutior in proprijs nec erat dum viueret agris,</l>
                  <l>Accipitres fugiens mitior illa feros.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:20150:19"/>
Si requiem quaeris volucrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> euadere morſus,</l>
                  <l>Ad quae confugias tecta columba vides.</l>
                  <l>Non capit exiguas volucrum regina columbas,</l>
                  <l>Praeda illi cerui, praeda futura draco.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In praiſe of the ſoueraigne and potent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe Queene Margaret of Spaine.</head>
               <p>There was painted the new moone, and a number of Elephants, acknowledging her for there benefactor: with this poſie: <hi>Vis beneficentiae &amp; virtutis.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cùm noua luna micat, magnorum turba Eleplantum</l>
                  <l>Fert teneros natos, lunam humileſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> colunt.</l>
                  <l>Tu noua luna micas tenebroſo Margaris orbi,</l>
                  <l>Iam ſentit radios Anglia nostratuos.</l>
                  <l>Ergo Britannigenae linquentes tecta paterna,</l>
                  <l>Ecce tuum lumen Cynthia ſancta colunt.</l>
                  <l>O ſalue rutilum ſydus Regina, Britannis</l>
                  <l>In caeca miſeris fulgida nocte mica.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>There was painted a bird bred in Germany, which ſhineth by night, flying ouer the ſea to Spaine, with this poſie. <hi>Nox ſicut dies illuminabitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quaenam haec quae toto ſpargens ſua lumina ponto,</l>
                  <l>Littus ad Heſperium per mare currit auis?</l>
                  <l>Illáne quam ignitis profert Germania pennis,</l>
                  <l>Quae tenebras noctis luce micante fugat?</l>
                  <l>Illa est: auratis collucens Margaris alis,</l>
                  <l>Huc noctis victrix, Austria fertur auis.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20150:19"/>
I propera Heſperio pulcherrima iungere ſoli,</l>
                  <l>Cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illo rutilae diuide lucis opus.</l>
                  <l>Sole, &amp; auc hac ornata, dies nocteſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> micabis</l>
                  <l>Heſperia, haec noctes ignit, &amp; ille dies.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>There was painted a high aſh tree with the leaues greene and pleaſant, and many ſerpentes flying from the ſhadow, with this poſie. <hi>Non hac latet anguis in herba.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sacra Ioui quercus, laurus pulcherrima Phoebo,</l>
                  <l>Conſecrat Auſtriacos Fraxinus alta duces.</l>
                  <l>Fraxineas metuit ſerpens perterritus vmbras,</l>
                  <l>Nec minus Austriacos haereſis hydra fugit.</l>
                  <l>Nae tu ſerpentum morſus Hiſpania temnas,</l>
                  <l>Auſtriacum dum te fraxinea vmbra tegit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>An Epigram to the Queens name.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>M</hi> argaris aequoreas gemmas praeit inclita gemm <hi>A</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> uſtriaco prognata ſolo, quam vincere cult <hi>V</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>R</hi> arus &amp; ipſe adamas neſcit, rutulanſue pyropu <hi>S,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>G</hi> ratiùs iſta micat, radiante<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> lumine vinci <hi>T,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> mouet illius noctem &amp; nigra nubila fulgo <hi>R</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>R</hi> eſplendens ſacra haec virtutis luce, profund <hi>I</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> mpia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hereſeon facit orbem linquere monſtr <hi>A</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>T</hi> erris reſtituens pietatis lumina, &amp; illi <hi>C</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> uſtriaci noua gemma, freti nitet aurea ſtell <hi>A.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Virgils aenigma.</head>
                  <l>Dic quibus in terris inſcripti nomina regum</l>
                  <l>Naſcantur flores, &amp; eris mihi magnus Apollo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20150:20"/>
                  <head>The aunſwer.</head>
                  <l>Ecce Maro Heſperijs flores naſcuntur in hortis,</l>
                  <l>Qui regum in folijs nomina ſcripta gerunt.</l>
                  <l>Margaris in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſos nomen nomen<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Philippi,</l>
                  <l>Anglorum flores Pincia vallis habet.</l>
                  <l>Martyribus reges hi nutriuere cruorem,</l>
                  <l>Et ſe purpureis inſeruere roſis.</l>
                  <l>Qui cruor effuſus pro religione tuenda,</l>
                  <l>Scribet in aeternis nomina tanta libris.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Spaniſh Copy are diuers other Epigrams which for breuities ſake I omit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="ceremony">
            <head>The coming of the Catholike Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces King Philippe the third, and Quene Margaret to the Ingliſh Colledge of Valladolid.</head>
            <p>THeire Mageſties ſome fewe dayes before their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Ingliſh Colledge, had viſited the cheife Religious houſes of this Citie, and in all places were receiued with ſo great preparation, ſpecially in the vniuerſitie; fower dayes before; that after ſo Royal entertainmentes this Colledge did feare &amp; not without reaſon, to appeare in theire Mageſties preſence, but that the litle gift of the widow ſo much eſteemed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for the good will and affection wherewith ſhe gaue it, did encorage the ſtudentes to doe the beſt they could: and ſo all thinges were put in order as aboue hath bene ſaid wher vpon S. Bernards day (which fell vpon a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20150:20"/>
ſunday) at two a clock in the afternoone came to the Colledge 24. of the Kings Garde, with theire ſargeant, who preſently deuided the ſoldiars at the gates, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe order that none ſhould enter, becauſe their Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties would that day, enioy the Colledge alone, and a litle after came the lieutenant of the Garde, who placed likewiſe other ſoldiars in all the roomes which were hung with verſes, with charge to keepe them, as they did, that none were wanting.</p>
            <p>The Steward of the kings howſe, and ſome other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciers, and gentlemen of the Pallace; vnderſtanding, that his M. would ſee the ſchollers chambers, and the manner of theire habitation, came before as the cuſtome is, and were much delited with the order and commoditie, to ſee that neither there was wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of any thing neceſſarie, nor any thing ſuperfluous, but as the widow had prouided for the Prophet Elizeus a bed, a table, a chaire, &amp; a light, ſo they had (euery one) all that was commodious for his ſtudies and reſt, without want or exceſſe.</p>
            <p>About fiue a clocke, or a litle after, came theire Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties to the Colledge, &amp; in ſigne of more confidence and good will, without theire accuſtomed garde, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they had diuers companyes both on foote and horſe lodged in the Citie which comonly wayte vpon them when they goe abroade. The ſtudentes expected them in the Church in two rankes, from the doore to the high altar, and the Prouinciall of the Societie being at the ſame tyme (by chaunce) in the Citie accompanyed with two Prieſtes of the Colledge, and reueſted (as the manner is in ſuch ſolemne receiuinges) attended theire Mageſties at the Church doore, who at theire enterance (hauing receiued holy water and kneeling downe vpon two cuſhens of cloth of gold which theire chaplens had there prouided) adoted the Crucifix which the father offered them, with ſo great reuerence and deuotion, as the Engliſh ſtudents there preſent were much moued to ſee it, who (as diuers of them afterwardes did confeſſe)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20150:21"/>
reioyced exceedingly to ſee thoſe two Monarkes of the world proſtate themſelues and adore with ſo great pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the Image of our Sauiour, for whoſe cauſe and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion they ſee them ſelues in baniſhment, theire parentes robbed and impriſoned, and many of their frendes perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and afflicted.</p>
            <p>In the meane tyme others of the ſtudents aboue in the quire ſang <hi>Te Deum laudamus,</hi> in theire accuſtomed Eccleſiaſtical Muſike which contented ſo much, as the Duke of Lerma and other noble men that came with the king; thought the ſingers had bene procured fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abroad, but vnderſtanding that it was the ordenarie muſike of the Colledge, and onely the ſtudentes, receiued double contentment to heare it, &amp; much more when at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance it was told them, that nothing was borrowed that day to receiue theire Mageſties but onely the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginges. The King and the Queene coming to the high altar remained there kneeling while the prieſt ended the verſicles and prayer accuſtomed to be ſung in the like receiuing of Princes; and after, they roſe on foot, and viewed the images of the three Ingliſh martyrs vpon the high altar which I mencioned before, and the Queene maruailing at the pictures which were in the hanginges of the church, the king told her they were the tormentes where-with the heretikes put to death the martyrs in England.</p>
            <p>Before they departed, vnderſtanding that the Relique which ſtood vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Altar was fleſh of the glorious Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr S. Alban that had endured without corruption aboue 12. hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeates, they both kneeled downe againe with great reuerence, and the Queene beſides her cuſhen vpon the ground to adore it, as they did both with ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affect and deuotion, as I muſt needes confeſſe to your highnes I was moued aboue meaſure to ſee it, and diuers others there preſent (as after-wardes I vnderſtood) no leſſe then I, with the ſame conſideration how king Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the 8. of England diſtroyed the holy Reliques of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20150:21"/>
glorious Martyr S. Thomas of Canterburie the honor of his kingdome and nation, ſeing the pietie and reuerence wherewithal our Catholike kinges did kyſſe and adore the Relique and fleſh of this holy Martyr of a forrayne countre and kingdome.</p>
            <p>As they paſſed out of the church, the ſchollers (who were all in order placed rounde about the firſt court) made altogether a low reuerence, and afterward by two and two went forward into the hall prepared (as I haue ſaid aboue) for theire Mageſties; who paſſing a long, veiwed with attention the Hietogliphicks and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and ſeamed to receiue contentment with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie and inuention: and paſſing on further, when the king ſaw them continue all the way as he went, in ſuch diuerſitie &amp; number (for they were aboue 270.) he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded they ſhould all be kept and brought him to the Palace, for that he would ſee them at leyſure, as he did.</p>
            <p>VVhen he entered the hall, the Muſicians in the other roome adioyning, deuided onely with a curtayn, began to play vpon theire vials and virginals a very graue and pleaſant ſong of eight partes, till theire Mageſties and thoſe that came in theire company were ſet, the ſchollers ſtood betweene the cloth of eſtate and the muſike in there rankes or companies, on the one ſide ſtood the Poetes and Rhetoricians: on the other, the Philoſophers, and in the middeſt the Prieſts &amp; diuines. And that they might be the better diſcerned, the firſt ranke was of the leaſt, in the ſecond were thoſe of middle ſtature, and in the third the talleſt; and the modeſtie and compoſition of all was ſuch as theire Mageſties did particularly note it, and were not a litle edified, to ſee together ſo many young youthes baniſhed for theire fidelitie to God and theire Religion, who altedy had offered vp theire labors, ſtudies and liues for the conuerſion of theire Countrie, liuing in collegial diſcipline with that example which theire very preſence did declare, and with ſo great puritie and innocencie of life, as ſtrangers of different nations
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20150:22"/>
(continuall witneſſes of all theire actions doe teſtifie) &amp; of ſo rare talents as the verſes and ingenious inuentions a bout the walls of the Colledge did ſhewe, and in fiue, of ſo good education and parentage, as might be ſeen in theire perſons, countenance and behauiour in ſo much as diuers Noblemen there preſent moued with this ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle, did wiſh they could bring vp theire children in the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, &amp; therefore diuers principall perſons of this real me haue procured very erneſtly and with great offers to haue theire ſonnes brought vp in this Seminaric, to learne the yertues which they ſee in the Ingliſh ſchollers, and truly in my iudgment there was nothing in all the ſolemnitie comparable to this ſight: and ſo would that famous Matron Cornelia Mother to the Graccos haue ſaid, if ſhe had bene preſent, who, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other Noble wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Rome gloried &amp; boſted in theire riches, vſed to bring forth her children modeſt and well nurtured, as the moſt pretious iewelles and greateſt riches that ſhe bad.</p>
            <p>VVhen theire Mageſties were ſett, and the Muſicians had ended, there came forth from amongſt the diuines, one of the ſtudents, who for the manifold giftes and graces which God hath beſtowed vpon him might well appeare in theire preſence, and kneeling downe vpon the one knee before the King in the middeſt of the hall, after his Mageſtie had giuen him ſigne to ariſe, ſtanding on foot ſaid as followeth in Latine.</p>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
               <head>The firſt Oration made to the Catholike King Philippe the third in the Ingliſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Valladolid.</head>
               <p>IN hoc hodierno conſpectu veſtro ornatiſsimo iucundiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> (Rex Maxime, Regina Sereniſsima) iure nobis foret optandum, quod Philoſophus quidam optaſſe dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20150:22"/>
ut Deus feneſtram aliquam in pectoribus noſtris ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riret, vt haec quae concepimus gaudia, non per anguſtas ſenſuum rimas emanarent, ſed patentibus pectorum por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis prorumperent: &amp; ipſi, geſtientem latitiam ſociorum meorum, non ex hilari eorum fronte conijceretis, ſed in intimo amoris fonte ſpectaretis. Nec enim nobis ſolum praebuiſtis nouum ſingularis laetitiae argumentum, verum etiam antiqui beneficij memoriam renouastis, memini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus enim (Philippe Rex potentiſsime) nec vnquam obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſcemur illius diei qui huic noſtro Seminarto omnium ornatiſsimus illuxit, non ſolis radijs, ſed tuis, &amp; Philippi parentis tui, &amp; clariſsimae ſororts, ſplendoribus illuſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: cuius diei adeo riuam imaginem hodierna preſentia veſtra animis noſtris obijcit, vt iterum intueri videmur Regem illum omnium ſaeculorum memoria maximum, in hoc ipſo loco, balbutientes puerulos tres integr as horas li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentiſsime audientem. Iterum cernimus quaſi oculis, ſanctiſsimum illum ac ſapientiſsimum Monarcham aeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te longuidum, ſed diuino amore feruidum alnmnos hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius Collegij ſuauiſsimis amplexibus &amp; vitali ſanctiſsimi pectoris ſpiritu, ad martyrium animantem. Verum non fuit ſatis hnmanitati tuae (ô magne Haeres non ſolum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternorum Regnornm, ſed etiam virtutum &amp; laudum) non fuit ſatis, quod Princeps Hiſpaniarum ſub Parentis tui vmbra hoc Seminarium ornaueris, niſi etiam hodier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no die, in haec anguſta tecta &amp; inornatos parietes, regium nomen et totum Maieſtatis tuae lumen inferres: niſi Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſsimum Auſtriacae Familiae decus, ſanctiſsimam coniu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gem Sereniſsimam Reginam adduceres, vt in vna exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum domuncula geminum orbis Sydus arderet.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:20150:23"/>
Moyſem puerulum èmatris gremie raptum &amp; inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſcirpea fiſcella, A Egyptij praecipitarunt in flumen, ex quo (diuino conſilio) a Pharaonis filia ereptus, Reginam habuit matrem, patrem Regem. Nos vero non A Egyptia, ſed maior haere ſum tyrannis è patrum ſinu &amp; matrum gremijs abſtractos, praecipitauit in Oceanum inſanis flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus hauriendos. Nil proficis A Egypte ſaeua, nil profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis; fluctuabit in freto haec ſcirpta cimba vſque ad Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num littus, &amp; ereptus inde puer, meliores inueniet pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, meliorem patrem. Intuemini igitur Parentes ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſsimi (permittite Maximi Principes it a vos ab or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; exulibus vocari) intuemimi natos veſtros, quos vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis non fortuna, ſed voluntas, non natura, ſed pietas pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit. Cerne (Rex Maxime) hos tuos filios, qui non ex ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno vtero nati fuimus, ſed ex aquis miſeriarum nata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uimus in hunc tuum paternum ſinum.</p>
               <p>Conijce ſereniſsimos oculos (Potentiſsima Pharaonis filia) in hos tuos Moyſes, quos ad ciues ſuos ex Egyptiacae ſeruitute liberandos, non inſcia &amp; inuita, ſed ſciens &amp; volens materna beneuolentia foues. Et quanquam quae accepimus benefitia adeo ſunt excellentia, vt ea vix opta re potuiſsemus; tamen vt à vobis longè praestantiora ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renius, eximia veſtra pietas &amp; virtus poſtulat.</p>
               <p>Creſcit enim quotidie (Inuicte Philippe) creſcit ex no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra calamitate, materia tuae beneficentiae ſeges tuae glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae. Quid enim illustrius, quid dignius Catholico nomine, magnitudine animi &amp; fortunae tuae, quam collegiſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſas reliquias fidei; donaſſe patria, ciuitate, domicilio, quos haereſes fecit extorres? Multorum eſt profecto Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac Caeſarum, hoſtes proſtraſſe armis, bello ſuperaſſe. Haec
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20150:23"/>
tua, &amp; ſanctiſsimi parentis tui ſingularis, &amp; omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſiſsima victoria, viciſſe beneficijs. Hic hodiernus cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae vestrae nouus &amp; inauditus triumphus (clariſsimi Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) in quo (caelo terráque applaudentibus) fulget gloria crucis, dum Religioms &amp; amoris vinculis tracti hi omnes ſocij mei ex remotiſsimis terris ad veſtrum patrocimum confugerunt, vt quorum alij potentiam metuunt, agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant &amp; praedicent benignitatem. Haec vos hominibus charos, haec Deo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimillimos redit, haec ampliora vobis Regna, haec nobiliora ſceptra dabit, in omnem aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem poſsidenda.</p>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
                  <head>The ſame in Engliſh.</head>
                  <p>AT this moſt glorious and moſt gratefull ſight of your Royal Mageſties (Mightie Monarcke, and moſt gratious Queene) iuſtly ſhould we wiſh that which a certayn phyloſopher is ſaid to haue wiſhed, that God had opened windowes in our breſtes, to the end your Mageſties might ſee the abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ioy we haue this day receaued, and not only gather it by our conntenance and wordes through the narrow chinckes of our exterior ſenſes, but rather behold it in our very hartes, as in the fountaine where it ſpringeth, for your maieſties haue not onely geeuen vs this newe occaſion of preſent gladnes, but alſo haue renewed the ioyfull memory of an other former fauour. VVe doe remember full well (moſt pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t king) neyther ſhall we euer be able to forget, that moſt glorious &amp; ſhining day, the brighteſt that euer was ſeene in this our Colledge, not with the preſence of the Sunne &amp; his beames, but of your royall Mageſty, and of the king your father of famous memory, to-gether with the renowned Lady the Infanta your ſiſter; which day,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20150:24"/>
this your preſence ſo reneweth, and in ſo liuely manner calleth it to memory, that it ſeemeth we ſee agayne that moſt glorious &amp; pious king memorable to all ages, in this very place, giuing eare againe to the ſtammering ſpeeches of children, as then he did, with ſingular curteſy &amp; attention, for three houres together. VVe ſee agayne in your Mageſtie, that moſt wiſe and potent monarch of the world, though then languiſhing in yeares, yet yonge and floriſhing in the loue of god &amp; zeale of his glory, how moſt louingly he embraced the ſchollers of this col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; with the liuely ſpirit of his pious and religious hart, incouraged them to martirdome. But all this ſemed nothing to your Royall benignitie (moſt worthy inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour not ſo much of your fathers kingdomes, as of his vertues and praiſes) you thought it not ſufficient to haue honoured this colledge with your preſence being then prince of Spaine, vnleſſe you ſhould this day agayne in your greateſt glory, ſtraiten your ſelfe within theſe nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row walles, bringing in your company her M. preſenc the honor and ornament of the houſe of Auſtria, that within this little colledge of baniſhed men, might be ſeene ſhining the Sunne &amp; Moone that giue light to the world.</p>
                  <p>The childe Moyſes, whome the tyrany of Egipt had violently drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mothers breaſtes almoſt the ſame howre he was borne, and caſt him into the riuer ſhut vp in a wicker baſket to ſeeke his aduentures, was by Gods eſpeciall prouidence found and taken vp by the daughter of Pharao, &amp; ſo came to haue a Queene for his mother and his father a kinge. we in like manner, are violently drawne &amp; driuen from our parentes, not by the Egiptian tyrany, but by another farre greater &amp; more cruell, by the hereſy of our country, which hath caſt vs headlong into the Ocean ſea to be drowned &amp; deuowred by the waues. But all in vayne (cruell Egipt) all in vayne, thy labour is loſt: for this our wicker boat, though toſſed for a whyle with the waues and billowes of the ſea, yet at laſt by the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20150:24"/>
ſame prouidence, is caſt on ſhore and aryued ſafe on the coaſt of Spayne, where the childe is taken vp, and hath found a new father and mother farre more noble and better then thoſe he loſt. Behold then pious and louing parents (giue this leaue moſt mighty princes to vs Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes baniſhed for Chriſte to call your Mageſties by this title) Behold I ſay, theſe your children, not geuen you by fortune, but adopted by your owne choyce; not yours by nature, but by your piety and religion behold mighty kinge theſe your ſonnes, not borne to your Mageſty out of our mothers wombes, but caried with the waters and waues of tribulation out of which we haue as if it were ſwomme into this your fatherly boſome. Caſt your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious eyes (potent daughter of Pharo) vppon theſe your Moyſes, whome with motherly affection you bringe vp, not as the other Queene did at vnawares, but witting and willingly, to deliuer their country from the Egiptian ſeruitude of hereſy and ſinne, and although the benifytes we haue already receiued, be ſo many &amp; ſo great, that we durſt ſcarſe ſo metymes haue wiſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet ſuch is your Mageſties piety &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty, that now it obligeth vs to hope for farr greater at your handes, for dayly there increaſeth (inuincible Philippe) there increaſeth dayly by our cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metie more &amp; more matter for your bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty: &amp; the harueſt groweth euery hower whereby you are to reape immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal glory (for what can be more glorious, or more agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to the name and title of a Catholike kinge, &amp; to the greatneſſe of your minde and fortune, then to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided country Citty and habitation, for thoſe whom he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy hath caſt out in baniſhment. Many other kinges and Emperours, haue ouercome their enemyes with armes, &amp; vanquiſhed them in warre: but this is your peculiar, and moſt glorious victory, &amp; of the king your father of holy memory to haue ouercom with curteſy and good deedes.</p>
                  <p>This preſent day place &amp; aſſembly is a triumph of your cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy (moſt renowmed Princes) in which the glory of Chriſt crucefied, is ſene, with ioy of heauen and earth, in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20150:25"/>
theſe my bretheren who drawen with cheines of loue &amp; Religion, are come from farre countries to liue vnder your protection, that they may acknowledge and teſtefy your bounty, whoſe greatneſſe others do feare. This me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe and clemency in ſo great power and Mageſtie, maketh you amiable to men &amp; like to God almighty, &amp; the ſame wil bring you greater dominons and far richer &amp; more noble ſceptors in heauen, then theſe which here you hold vpon earth, to be yours for al eternety.</p>
                  <p>The ſtudent that made this Oration deliuered it with ſo good grace and action, and with ſuch modeſtie mixt with the affectes and feelinge of that he ſpake, as it was much lyked of all that were preſent and holden for a good beginning of the reſt that was to follow. At the end of this oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> while the orator went to kiſſe the king his hand, the curtaine was drawne that couered the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, &amp; for that the voices in the quire, which I ſpoke of before &amp; the muſicke of inſtrumentes, at there Maieſties entrance into the hall had cauſed curioſity in them and the reſt, and deſire to ſee who they were that had ſonge and played, they were not a litle contented when the curtayne was drawne, ſeeing as before had bene told them that they were only the ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, without any other help from a broad, who now in ſight with there modeſty and good preſence, gaue double grace to that they did, &amp; ſo with inſtrumentes and voices together, begone an other ſonge of thoſe which they vſe in there high maſſes of excellent muſique which begone <hi>Domine Deus virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> and ended <hi>Beatus homo qui ſperat in te,</hi> and towardes the end of this muſike came forth from amongſt the yongeſt company a litle youth that in ſemblance ſeemed a very angell, who with great grace and making a low courteſie to there Maieſties, went vp to the pulpet which (as I ſayd before) was prepared ouer againſt the cloth of eſtate. This childes father ſeeing him ingenious &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to vertue, notwithſtanding he was his eldeſt ſonne deſired (as him ſelfe told me) that rather he ſhould loſe his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20150:25"/>
inheritance then his faith and Religion; and moreouer ſeeing him of ſo tender and delicate complexion, as it would be dangerous to ſend him a long iourney alone or not very well accompanied, he determined although it were with daunger of his liuing and life to bringe him out of England him ſelfe to this Seminary, as he did, and here in the Church vpon his ariuall (like another Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham that had come to this hill to ſacrifice his dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Iſaac) offered him vp to our ſauiour before the bleſſed ſacrament, with ſo great zeal and deuotion that he edified all the Colledge; to ſee the great force of the grace of God, and how it ouercometh and ſubiecteth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and all humane difficulties, as in this &amp; many other heroicall workes of theſe faithfull Catholikes of Ingland is euident. A few dayes after the father departid with great comfort to leaue his ſonne in ſuch ſecuritie, and the child remained ſo mery and contented and with ſo good lyking of the Colledge, as if he had bene in his fathers houſe, and without going abroad in one yeare he learned the Spaniſh tonge. And truely if to S. Ierome it ſeemed a thing worthy of admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that a philoſopher of whom he wryteth, vndertooke a longe and daungerous iourney to heare Socrates: much more would he maruaile if he liued in theſe our dayes, to ſee not onely philoſophers &amp; men of ripe age, but children of ſo tender yeares as this &amp; many others, to paſſe the ſeas, &amp; in ſo great and manifeſt labours and daungers as they doe, to come to this and the other Seminaries, onely to learne and conſerue the Catholike faith, and with ſo difficult a purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torne to teach it in there country where it muſt coſt them ſo deare, as the world knoweth, and all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any temporall hope or commodity to them ſelues: and therefore with a far more excellent and glorious end, then was that of the Philoſopher. This youth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the pulpet, and haueing made low reuerence to there Maieſties, begonne in Spaniſh this breefe ſpeech or Preface that followeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20150:26"/>
               <head>The Preface to the ten tonges.</head>
               <p>THe holy ghoſte hauing (with ſingular prouidence) determined to bring the whole world to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſte, and that his name &amp; glory ſhould he publiſhed through-out the earth by the holy Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Apoſtles; gaue them for this end diuers ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and languages, that with them his greatnes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie might more eaſily be made knowne to all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, accordinge to this, we fyndinge our ſelues moſt highly bound and obliged to your Maieſties, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to declare our gratitude to the whole world, haue endeuoured to imitate this paterne and example of the holy ghoſt, with deſire (if your Maieſties giue vs leaue) to ſignifie in diuers tonges and in the beſt manner we can that which we ſhal neuer be able ſufficiently to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe of our owne obligation, nor of your Maieſties greatnes; both which the Prophet Dauid hath combined in one, and moſt liuely deſcribed in the twenteth Pſalme: which Pſalme made by a king and meant of the king of kinges, dooth in ſuch manner lay before vs the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions which your Maieſties haue receaued of God, &amp; to Heroical and Royal vertues wherewith you procure to imitare the ſoueraine kinge, the Prophet and true pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of kinges, of whome the Pſalme ſpeaketh that all that in it is ſayed may very fitly be applied to you, as ſhal appeare in the diſcourſe which we wil proſecute in ten different languages, obſeruing the breuitie due to your Maieſties preſence, and begin which the Spaniſh as the moſt familiar and beſt knowne, that it may open the way and after ſerue to enterpret the reſt. The Queene and ſome other ladies of the court, by a certaine occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ſome dayes before heard of this litle youth, and ſo were deſirous to ſee him, and heard him with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary contentment and applauſe, and the Pſalme choſen in the opinion of all that were preſent, fitted maruailou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly well the intent and obligation of the tyme and place, and ſo preſently, there went vp to the pulpet another ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20150:26"/>
brought vp in the Seminaryes ſince he was ſix yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res old, who with all the reſt that followed obſerued the ſelfe ſame manner of curteſy, makeing firſt a low reuerence downe to the bottome of the pulpet, and the like as often as they ſpake to there Maieſties, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companing his ſpeach (as the reſt alſo did) with graue and modeſt action, begonne the firſt vearſe of the Pſalme and the explication in Spaniſh that followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Domine in virtute tua laetabitur Rex &amp; ſuper ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare tuum exultabit vehementer.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pſal. 20.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>The Ingliſh of the Spaniſh tongue.</head>
               <p>The propet Dauid in the beginning of this Pſalme diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth two fountaines, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce floweth the trew ioy &amp; comfort of all kinges: the firſt is, <hi>in virtute tua lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabitur Rex.</hi> The king which putteth his truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence not in his owne wiſdome, nor in his treaſures not in his forces &amp; ſtrength, but in the power and protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of almighty God, findeth him ſelf ſo potent that no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie ſucceſſe can diſmay him; ſo rich that he fealeth no want of gold or ſiluer: ſo armed that he feareth not eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, though neuer ſo many: and ſo ſtrong that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth alwaies in proſperity, and comfort without feare. for though the world, and all they that truſt therein be ſubiect to changes, and that dayly experience doth ſhew, yet he that truſteth in God is ſure to ſtand, and to enioy endleſſe and vnſpeakable comfort.</p>
               <p>A ſecond &amp; greater conſolation which this our king may expect (&amp; Dauid ſaith iſſueth from the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) is, that he procuring the ſaluation of ſoules, and to propagate not ſo much his owne dominions as the kingdome of Chriſt our ſauiour, he giueth him parte of his owne felicity and ioy as to a companion &amp; partaker of his enterpriſe in the world; and ſo ſaieth the prophet
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20150:27"/>
that this ioy and conſolation ſhal be moſt aboundant, <hi>Es ſuper ſalutare tuum exaltabit vehementor.</hi> O how great thinges may your maieſties hope for at gods handes ſith your truſt in him and your holy zeale; to inlarge the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion is ſo great, that you haue not put <hi>non plus vltra</hi> in Spaine, but extend it beyond the fardeſt ſeas, to the eaſt and weſt and to the north from whence we come to ſee and reuerence this new Salomon, &amp; finde his wiſdome and vertues to be more then ſame did tel vs. Enlarge then o happy and fortunat Spaine the foldes of thy hart, for thy ioyes ſhal increaſe like the ſea, &amp; drowne thearin the enimies of the Catholike church. Theſe two proprieties of the good king the prophet Dauid follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in this Pſalme, which ſhal be declared brefly to your maieſties in ten tounges; where of ſom are profeſled in this Seminary &amp; to the end that thoſe which ar not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode, may notwithſtanding be gratfull to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, I ſhall declare them with the breuitie I can, and ſo I ende the Spainſh, with theſe wordes of the holie ghoſt, <hi>Beata terra cuius Rex nobilis eſt.</hi> Bleſſed is that coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try, and happy art thou o Spaine which haſt a king of ſo noble a minde and of ſo high and holy cogitations.</p>
               <p>This explication of the firſt verſe being ended, the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent went downe and placed him ſelfe below neare the pulpit, ouer againſt ther maieſties, to declare the tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that ſhould neede interpretation.</p>
               <p>Here I could certifie your highnes of ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of particular contentment, and edification con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the other nine ſtudentes that followed; but not to be tedious to your highnes I will heere paſſe in ſilence diuers thinges worthy to be knowen, and come to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond that ſpoke in the Hebrew tonge, who obſeruing the natural guttural pronuntiation of that language expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſecond verſe of the Pſalm which followeth.</p>
               <div type="speech">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20150:27"/>
                  <head>The Hebrew.</head>
                  <q>Deſiderium cordis eius tribuiſti ei, &amp; voluntate la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biorum eius non fraudaſti eum.</q>
                  <p>Although the tounge in it ſelfe was ſo harde to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, neuertheleſſe with the conuenient actions he gaue it, and the reuerences he made to there Maieſties when he ſpake vnto them, lifting vp his eyes to heauen when he mentioned God, and other actions which in parte ſignified what he ſpake, but ſpecially with hope of the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promiſed: notwithſtanding it might be thought that theſe vnknowne tonges would be leſſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull, yet the euent ſhewed the contrary: at the end of euery ſpeache, the orator made low curteſy to there Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, and in the meane time the other that followed, was readie to goe vp to the pulpit, and prepared him ſelf to ſpeake, whileſt the interpreter below declared that which had allreddy bin ſaid as he did the Hebrew in the ſence following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Interpreter.</head>
                  <p>The Hebrew tonge hath declared breifly the happy ſucceſſe which Dauid prophecieth to the good king: to wit, that he can aſke nothing of God which he ſhall not obtaine, binding almighty God in obligation of promiſe to fulfill his deſires, as he in all thinges procureth to doe Gods holy wil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Greke tongue.</head>
                  <p>The Greke tongue begun taking the third verſe for his theame.</p>
                  <q>Quoniam praeuenisti cum in benedictionibus dulcedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, poſuiſti in capite eius coronam de lapide pretioſo.</q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:20150:28"/>
VVhen he and the reſt in ſeuerall tongues named this king they did it with ſo proper and magnificent titles, accompanyed with ſuch reuerence, that it was graetfull to thoſe that heard only the ſound, though they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not the ſignification of the wordes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Interpreter.</head>
                  <p>He hath ſaid in Greke that God almighty doeth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſuch a king with bleſſinges of ſweetnes, giuing him from his tender yeares ſuch prudence, valour, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of nature, that his gouerment is gratefull &amp; giueth contentment to all, and putteth vpon his head a crowne of pretious ſtones, which Salomon in an other place <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb.</hi> 12. declareth in theſe wordes: <hi>Mulier diligens, coronae est viro ſuo:</hi> ſo as the Margaret or iewel here preſent, doeth not ſuffer vs to doubt of what precious ſtone the Prophet meant.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
                  <head>The Latine tongue.</head>
                  <q>Vitam petijt ate, &amp; tribuisti longitudinem dierum in ſaeculum ſaeculi.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the fourth place went vp a young man of honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parents by blood, and much more for theire conſtant profeſſion of the Catholyk faith, who came to this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie through many daungers by ſea; and enemies. By his countenance and perſon he ſhewed well who he was, and with a grateful voice and action ſpake to the king as followeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>ETiamſi videamus Maieſtatem tuam (Rex potentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime) in ipſo beatiſsimae vitae flore verſari, tamen cum Regij pectoris tui humana omnia deſpicientis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitudinem intuemur, adduci non poſſumus, vt creda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus inuictum illum &amp; caelestem animum vitam cadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20150:28"/>
&amp; fluxam à Deo optimo maximo petijſſe. Illud ſanè certum &amp; exploratum habemus, te cum vastum impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium à Philippo parente, velut à ſanctiſsimo Dauide foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſsimus Salomon accepiſses, impetrato à ſummo Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce &amp; miſſo per omnes Hiſpanias pleniſsimo inbilaeo publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis &amp; priuat is tuis &amp; aliorum precibus ſapientiam qua populum tuum regeres postulaſſe: audi igitur (Rex Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholice) Deum, optimum, maximum ijſdem verbis, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus olim Salomoni reſponſa dantem ſanctiſsimis tuis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulatis. Quia, inquit, non petijsti dies multos, nec diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias, ſed ſapientiam ad diſcernendum iudicium; ecce dedi tibi cor ſapiens &amp; intelligens in tantum, vt nullus ante te ſimilis tui fuerit, nec post ſurrecturus ſit. Quantae enim pietatis ſapientiae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt in ſumma rerum omnium potestate in adoleſcentiae flore non abripi ventis licentiae, &amp; aetatis, ſed integras nationes locis diſiunctiſsimas, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus diſsimillimas, numero propemodum infinitas, veluti vnius corporis membra in pace, &amp; officio continere: ſed pergit Deus; etiam, inquit, quae non postulaſti dedi tibi, diuitias ſcilicet &amp; gloriam, vt nemo fuerit ſimilis tui in regibus cunctis retro diebus: quod quàm rectè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onueniat in maiestatem tuam ex eo ſat is constat, quod ipſum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomonem imperij magnitudine &amp; opum affluentia ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raueris. Si autem, inquit, ambulaueris in vijs meis ſicut Dauid pater tuus, longos faciam dies tuos. Quid m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur gratulemur maiestati tuae dies longos, imperium faustum &amp; diuturnum (foeliciſsimè Salomon) qui ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſsimi genitoris tui pietatem ſic es aemulatus, vt ſenem iuuenis quodammodo ſuperaſſe videaris: Nec est quod de perpetuo foelicitatis tuae curſu dubitemus, cum non poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20150:29"/>
de pietatis tuae constantia dubitare. It aque de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestate tua ad Deum conuerſi vere pronunciamus: vit am petijt àte, &amp; tribuisti ei in hoc mundo vitam, ſapientia, opibus, gloria abundantem, &amp; dabis in caelo, vt ſperemus vitam ſempiternam, longitudinem dierum in ſaeculum ſaeculi.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The ſame in Ingliſh.</head>
                  <p>ALthough (moſt mighty and potent King) we ſee your Maieſty in the very prime and flower of this your happy age, yet not-withſtanding when we conſider your magnanimity. and the greatnes of your Royal mynde which diſpiſeth all humane and earthly thinges, we cannot beleeue that you haue aſked of God almighty this fraile and vnſtable life, but that when you were to take the gouernement of your kingdomes from the renowmed king your father, as an other Salomon from king Dauid, and procured from his holynes a Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley and ſent it through all your dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, we are perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that both by publique and priuat prayers by your owne and by the prayers of others. you aſked of God as Salomon did, wiſdome, to gonerne this your people. Harken then moſt Catholike king the anſwere of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to your petition in the very ſame wordes wherewith he anſwereth king Salomon: becauſe (ſaith hee) thou haſt not aſked of me long lyfe or riches but wiſedome to iudge aright: behold therefore I haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the a hart full of wiſedome &amp; vnderſtanding, ſo that none hath bin before like vnto thee nor ſhall ariſe after thee how great a ſigne of piety and wiſedome is it in your Maieſty to ſtand vpon the hight of ſo great power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctority in the weakeſt &amp; moſt vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant part of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s age ſo ſtedfaſt &amp; vnmooueable, as not to be ouerthrowne with the greateſt blaſts of libertie and youth, but to kepe your
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20150:29"/>
ſelf irreprehenſible and ſo many nations as you gouerne ſo far a ſunder, and of ſo different diſpoſition &amp; manners ſo ſubiect to you as they be, and vnited amongeſt them ſelues in peace, and concorde, as members of one body. But God almighty paſſeth on farther with your Maieſty, and ſaieth; riches and honour which thou haſt not aſked thoſe alſo I doe giue thee, that none ſhal be like thee amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt al the kinges of the earth: which promiſe how it is fulfilled in your Maieſtie may wel appeare, in that you do far excel and ſurpaſſe king Salomon in greatnes of dominion and aboundance of riches: But (ſaieth God) yf thou ſhalt walk in my commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as Dauid thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did, I will multiply thy daies vpon the earth: why then may we not congratulate with your Maieſty a long and happy lyfe, and a floriſhing, proſperous, and permanent raigne (moſt fortunate Salomon) who ſo imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate your fathers vertues, as in theſe young yeares you ſtriue to excel him, neither can we feare the continuance of your proſperity, which we ſo much deſire and pray for, ſeing the conſtancy of your pietie and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therefore tuurning vs to God we may very well ſay of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that which the Prophet hath ſaid in this verſe; <hi>Vitam petijt àte, &amp; tribuiſti ei longitudinem dierum in ſeculum ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi,</hi> he hath aſked life and thow haſt giuen it him aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with wiſdome riches and glory in this world, &amp; we hope your Maieſty ſhal receiue in heauen euerlaſting life and length of daies for euer and euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Corniſh tongue.</head>
                  <q>Magna est gloria eius in ſalutare tuo, gloriam &amp; magnum decorem impones ſuper eum.</q>
                  <p>In this tongue ſpake a young man borne in that parte of England, which is toward Britanny, and the language is as far different from the Engliſh as here in Spaine the Biſcay tongue from that of Caſtile, and hath a certaine
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20150:30"/>
grace and reddynes of ſpeach not vnlike to that of the Biſcaies, his ſpeach was ſhort, &amp; he deliuered it very well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Interpreter.</head>
                  <p>He hath ſaid in his language that many men prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de glorie and honor, but few do find it, becauſe the moſt parte of men ſeeke it where it is not, in vaine oſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in the deceitfull ſhew of the world and ſo at length, ſee them ſelues deceiued, for trew honour is to be found only in vertue and trew religion, where your Catholike Maieſties ſeeke it, and therefore it followeth you as the ſhadow followeth the body of him that goeth towards the Sunne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Engliſh.</head>
                  <p>One of the ſtudents ſpake in his natural language with great liuelynes, eloquence, and proprietie of action, and vſed ſo ſignificant wordes, diuers of them correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the latine, as the moſt parte of that he ſpake was vnderſtood, and for his theame he took the verſe follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</p>
                  <q>Quoniam dabis ei in benedictionem in ſeculum ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, laetificabis cum in gaudio cum vultu tuo.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Interpreter.</head>
                  <p>He hath ſaid in Ingliſh that this eternal benediction which the Prophet Dauid foretelleth in this verſe, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſeth to a good king, is no other then to defend, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate, and encreaſe the Chriſtian religion, which is the greateſt dignity and honor that God almighty hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon your Maieſties. For the other bleſſings you haue receiued as the foyſon of the earth, the treaſure of your kingdomes, and all other temporal commodities vaniſh a way as the dew ſtrucken with the Sunne bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20150:30"/>
but this other benediction is immoueable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent, like to the Sunne it ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The welſche tongue.</head>
                  <p>In this tongue ſpake a Preiſt borne in that Prouince, who not long after was to go into England, and had for his theame theſe two verſes following.</p>
                  <q>Quoniam Rex ſperat in Domino, &amp; in miſericordia altiſsimi non commouebitur.</q>
                  <q>Inueniatur manus tua omnibus inimicis tuis, dextera tua inueniet omnes qui te oderunt.</q>
                  <p>He deliuered his ſpeach ſo deuoutly and confidently as if he had had commiſſion from heauen to promiſe the good ſucceſſe he fore-told to there Maieſties, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence countenance and action moued all to deuotion, &amp; more thoſe that knew him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Interpreter.</head>
                  <p>He hath ſaid in welſh that this king hauing for his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and ſheild the mercie of God, ſhal infallibly ſubdue all his enemyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Flemmiſh.</head>
                  <p>He that ſpake in flemmiſh in his pronunciation and manner of ſpeaking, ſeemed a natural flemming and had for his theame this verſe that followeth.</p>
                  <q>Pones cos vt clibanum ignis in tempore vultus tui, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus in ira ſua conturbabit eos &amp; deuorabit eos ignis.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Interpreter.</head>
                  <p>He hath ſaid in flemmiſh that one great point of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and dignity of this king is, that he hath the ſame
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20150:31"/>
cauſe, the ſame enimies, and the ſelf ſame puniſhment for them which God hath prepared for his enemies in hel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The French tongue.</head>
                  <p>The French tongue was very wel liked, partly for that the youth ſpake it with the naturall pronunciation of the language, and partly becauſe his Maieſty vnderſtandeth it wel, and him ſelfe did interpret to the Queene the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that which was ſaid, and ſo there was no neede of interpretter heere, not for the latin and Italian to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The French had for this theame this verſe following.</head>
                  <q>Fructum eorum de terra perdes, &amp; ſemen eorum à filijs hominum.</q>
                  <p>This verſe of the twenteth Pſalme of the prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid (moſt puiſant Monarch of the world) which at this time I haue taken to diſcourſe vpon, may ſeeme very fit for this purpoſe, to declare and ſet forth your inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diligence in withſtanding, ſubduing, and rooting out hereſy, and this not only in your owne kingdomes and dominions, where no heretike dare appeare or lift vp his head: but alſo in the countries about you; <hi>Fructum eorum de terra perdes &amp; ſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eorum à filijs hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> you doe extirpat and root out there fruite, that is, the vices &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes proceeding from there wicked doctrine, reducing there ſeede to the Catholik faith by your care and ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; in teſtimony where-of may be aleaged the peace concluded in france, the continuall wars in Flanders, and moſt of all our miſerable country of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, towards the which your loue and affection alwayes hath bin, &amp; now is, ſo great that no tongue is able to declare it; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides your great vigilance &amp; care taken to conclude ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and peace after ſo long war (which only hereſy hath cauſed and continued) who can ſufficiently admire your
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20150:31"/>
Maieſties fauour more then humaine, in erecting and maintayning not only two colledges here in Spaine, this &amp; that of Siuil, but alſo two others in Flanders, the one at Doway, the other at S. Omers as it were fower ſpiritual bulwarkes &amp; fortreſſes to repreſſe and ſubdue the malice of the heretikes, and as a holſome hearbe calleth Britta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, to chaſe a way &amp; put to flight thoſe venemous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes, the infernal ſpitites that haue infected and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned England with hereſy; wherefore very wel may this verſe be applied to your maieſtie <hi>Fructum eorum de terra perdes &amp; ſemen eorum à filijs hominum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="speech">
                  <head>The Italian tongue.</head>
                  <p>The Italian with the ſweetnes of the tongue it ſelf, &amp; the good grace that the orator gaue it, ſeemed wel choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the laſt verſe of the Pſalme, &amp; becauſe it agreeth with the Latin and Spaniſh, it was vnderſtood of all and needed no interpreter his theame was this, <hi>Exalt are domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in virtute tua cantabimus &amp; pſallemus virtutes tuas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Although the reſt of the Pſalme fitteth ſo well the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and place as your Maieſtie hath heard, yet may it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that this laſt verſe maketh not ſo much for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſeing the Catholike Church our mother ſo affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, our moſt deare country ſo ouerrun with hereſies, that the wicked triumph and, the faithful ſuffer, our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and freindes robbed, impriſoned, tormented and cruelly mattered. VVho conſidering this, wil not iudge that we ſhould rather cry out with the Prophet Ieremy. <hi>Vide domine quoniam tribulor ſubuerſum eſt cor meum in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipſo, quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amaritudine plenus ſum.</hi> And ſo might wee with all reaſon if it were not (moſt noble and pious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce) that your Catholike and Royal hart is ſo reddy to hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe vs, as all the world knoweth. But now what maruel is it hauing here preſent your Maieſtie our moſt gracious protector and refuge, that forgetting the teares and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes which our baniſhment requireth, we reioyce and be glad for your Maieſties felicity prayſing God, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20150:32"/>
him infinite thankes for the great fauours and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites he hath beſtowed vpon you and ſaying with the Prophet Dauid. <hi>Exaltare domine in virtute tùa.</hi> Extol the powerful hand of the almighty that hath placed your Royall dignity as a ſtrong forte againſt all the enimies of his holy Church, and a refuge and comfort of all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Catholikes, in ſo much that where your Maieſty rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneth, there Catholike religion, and the faith of Chriſt floriſheth: for this (moſt potent king) we ar glad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice for your power and greatnes, and can do no leſſe but praiſe and thanke the eternal Maieſtie of our ſauiour, that in ſo troubleſome and daungerous a time hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided ſo ſure a hauen for vs, and for his Church, ending the Pſalme with the wordes of the Prophet, <hi>Cantabimus &amp; pſallemus virtutes tuas:</hi> At the end of this Pſalme the Prophet ſeemeth to inuite and oblige thoſe that enioy the fauour and protection of the good king, whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had deſcribed, to ſing and ſhew forth his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie and felicity and ſo the Engliſh ſtudents began a ſweet and artificial ſong made after their country manner of muſicke and the ditty in Spaniſh to the purpoſe, which one of them ſtanding betweene the two ſettes of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes ſung in ſight of there Maieſties, and the Ingliſh muſicke with the Spaniſh ditty gaue extraordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to all, and no leſſe when on a ſoddaine they ſaw appeare in the pulpit the childe that in the beginning made the introduction to the tongues, and ſo all were ſilent, and attentiue to heare him, and he perceiuing him ſelfe to be heard with fauour took hart and ſpake with much more audacity and better grace then in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The concluſion and thankes to ther Maieſties.</head>
               <p>In teſtimonie of the ſingular loue and affection which we do acknowledge and moſt humbly reuerence in your Maieſties, this ſhall ſuffiſe to all the world, that a childe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20150:32"/>
dare preſume and be ſo bold as to ſpeake in preſence of the Monarch thereof neuertheleſſe who would not take hart and be encoraged with ſo eſpecial fauour &amp; cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, ſeing ſo great a Maieſtie and highnes humble and include him ſelfe with in the ſtraite and lowly wales of this poore Colledge of baniſhed Catholikes, only to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and comfort them with his Royal preſence. And if the Biſhops and Prelats of the Nicene counſail who had ſuffered in the defence of the ſame faith and religion that we profeſſe, receiued ſo great comfort with the loue and eſtimation which the moſt Chriſtian and religious Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror Conſtantine the great ſhewed them for the ſame reſpect, not only embraceing them, but moſt humbly kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the markes and tooke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the tormentes which they had ſuffered, what ioy may your Maieſtie thinke that my bretheren and companions doe receiue, ſeing them ſelues ſo highly fauoured and honoured with ſo many ſignes of your ſingular affection, and with the fauorable preſence of the Queenes Maieſtie, wherewith we finde our ſelues much more animated; then diſmaied with the cruel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of our country, and if the like courteſy and loue ſhewed to theſe Seminaries by your fathers, &amp; your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Royall clemencie in times paſt, did ſo confirme and encourage them which receiued thoſe fauours that they feared not to ſhead moſt valerouſly theire blood in the flower of theire youth, for teſtimony and defence of the holy Catholike faith ſuffring cruel martirdome as well-nygh two hundred of our Prieſts haue done for the ſame cauſe, and ſome of this Seminary ſince your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties laſt being here eight yeares agoe: to what victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries then, to what triumphes do theſe newe aboundant fauoures cal and inuite vs (moſt courteous and religious Princes?) me thinkes I feel the blood boyling in my companions hartes, offring it ſelfe to be ſhed for Ieſu Chriſt, for whoſe ſake we ſee our ſelues this day ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of your Maieſties: And if it ſhall pleaſe God to giue any of vs ſo good fortune, our blood ſhall cry to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20150:33"/>
heauen, aſking crownes of euerlaſting rewarde for your Maieſties, and in the earth proclaiming and publiſhing the Chriſtian zeale and piety of the Catholike Kinges of Spaine.</p>
               <p>The Eſtrich is of ſo groſſe &amp; cruel condition that ſhee forſaketh her young ones before they come out of the ſhell, but (not without eſpecial prouidence of god) they are hatched and brought vp with the heat of the Sunne, what els is our lamentable country but the ſame vnkinde Eſtrich (which the prophet Ieremy lamenteth, ſaying the daughter of my people is cruel like the Eſtrich in the wildernes that forſaketh her young ones before they be hatched: ſo in this our deſolation and baniſhment he nouriſheth fauoureth and foſtereth vs as a father who by office &amp; title is the Sunne of Spaine. And if Moyſes who after was to be the captaine of Gods people had good for tune (as afore hath bin ſaid) when he was a childe that being caſt into the water to periſh, he was found by the kinges daughter of Egipt &amp; by her adopted for her owne, our good fortune is no leſſe but grater then his, to fall here into the handes of your Maieſties, and in Flanders into the handes of the Infant of Spaine. In times paſt Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was beholding to Spaine for gold ſiluer, pearles, oyle, wine, and the like fruites of the earth, but now for other fruites and riches much more pretious then gold or ſiluer, the fruites of faith and Catholike religion and all kinde of vertues and ieuells of heauen. Oh that the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious troope of martirs of theſe Seminaries wold come downe to giue your Maieſties thankes for the fauours, which in time of this ſo great neceſſity and perſecution you ſhew to the Ingliſh Catholikes, and bring you from heauen the enſignes and ornamentes of triumph which there are prouided for your maieſties in recompence of the education of ſo many martirs, and the honor done to them vpon earth. Oh that they would come and giue vp to your Maieſties handes the Palmes of victory &amp; glory now in your life time, which ſhal be brought you when
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20150:33"/>
you depart out of this world. I dare vndertake you would remaine contented, &amp; we ſatiſfied to ſee our duty and obligation in part diſcharged. but ſeing this my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire taketh not effect, I beſeche moſt humbly the king of kinges, in behalf of all my companions preſent, &amp; abſent that he vouchſafe to receiue your maieſties, with as great loue and liberality in his kingdome, as you haue receiued and fauored vs in yours for his ſake.</p>
               <p>The childe pronounced this oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſo tender affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, ſhewing himſelfe to feel that which he ſpake in ſuch ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, that theire Mageſties &amp; all that were preſent were exceedinghly mooued, and diuers could not forbeare teares. After the oration he came downe from the pulpit, &amp; hauing made his reuerence went to kiſſe the Kinges hand, who with his accuſtomed cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce embraced him, ſhewing in his countenance how wel he had lyked his ſpeach. After him followed the reſt of the ſtudents to whome alſo his Maieſty ſhewed ſuch fauour and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie as wel appeared that God almighty had brought them out of theire fathers houſes &amp; country in whoſe hand are the harts of Catholike kings, to encline them as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to fauour his workes.</p>
               <p>About the middeſt of the laſt oration entered the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges pages with torches lighted which they had brought from the pallace, becauſe it was night, and when theire Maieſties aroſe to depart the father of the Colledge went to the cloth of eſtate to giue them thankes, &amp; beſought the king that he would vouchſafe to continew alwayes his accouſtumed fauour &amp; protection to this holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, whereunto he anſwered, that he had care to doe it, &amp; that he knew it was much to Gods honour and ſeruice of the Church, and therfore could doe no leſſe.</p>
               <p>The noble men and courtiers that went forth before theire Maieſties could not diſſemble the contentment they had receiued, and in particular the Marqueſſe of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lada the kings great Steward affirmed that in all the progreſſes and iournies he had accompanied him and his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20150:34"/>
father, they had neuer bin in any place more nobly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and required copyes of all the orations, and of the interpretations that had bin made vpon the Pſalme, and the Duke of Lerma deſirous to ſee the ſtudent which he maintayneth in the Colledge, embraced him in the kinges preſence with ſuch tender affection, as if he had bin his owne father, and told there Maieſties that he adopted him for his Sonne, and that it was reaſon the Queene ſhould alſo take ſome number to her charge, wherevnto ſhe anſwered, that alredy ſhee had purpoſed to do it. Theire Maieſties when they came into the vter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt court, for that it was darke and the multitude of thoſe that acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied them ſhadowed the ſtudents, who were placed in the way in the ſame order, as when theire Maieſties entered into the Colledge, one of the noble men ſeeing them, as the pages lifted vp their torches ſayed to the Duke of Lerma, look (my lord) what a goodly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Eccleſiaſticall men, and he ſaid to the king, will your Maieſtie ſee a quire of angells, whereat the kinge and the Queene turning to the ſchollers with ſignification of a courteous fare-well, they alltogether made reuerence to thire Maieſties, and the Duke much moued with the ſight, wringing one of the fathers of the Colledge that went with him by the hand, ſayed a lowd, it is impoſſible that Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhould miſcary that bringeth forth ſuch childeren.</p>
               <p>All the nobilitie, maides of honor, and gentlemen of the court that had bin preſent departed, commending greatly that which they had ſeene, and as the king was to go out of the gate the Rector kiſſed his hand, crauing pardon that he had kept him ſo long, whereunto he au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; that the tyme had not ſeemed long, and that all had contented him exceedingly. There was gathered a great multitude of gentlemen, and others of the citie before the Colledge, maruailing much to ſee theire Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſtay ſo long within, and ſo late in the night with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theire guard, and much more when they ſaw the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20150:34"/>
of contentment in them, and all the reſt at their comming forth, and ſo the ſame night diuers prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal perſons that could not that day come into the Colledge, deſired that nothing might be taken downe, till the next day following, when many learned men of the Vniuerſitie, Religious, and others, and gentlemen of the citie, came to read the verſes, and ſee how their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties had bin receiued, &amp; ſeemed no leſſe ſatisfied then the others the day before. Thankes be giuen to almighty God, that can finde meanes to comfort &amp; honour thoſe that bee perſecuted, &amp; diſhonoured for his holy name.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>An aduertiſement to the Catholikes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, of the preſent ſtate of their children brought vp in this Colledge of Vallado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and of the comfort they may worthely expect of them heer-after.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe I aſſure my ſelf that your highines hath inhereted not the leaſt part of your fathers loue and affection to the Catholikes of England, and that you deſire to keep freſh his glorious memorie with them no leſſe gratfull then the memorie of the good king Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias was to the people of Iſraell, and becauſe the rigorous perſecution they ſuffer cauſeth in all good Catholikes great compaſſion and deſyre, to comfort ſo valorous and faythfull people, and that nothing can bee more gratefull to good parents then to heare newes of their childeren, hoping that this relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may come to their handes, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted into Ingliſh by your highneſſe comaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I haue thought good to adde ſome particular things of this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie, for their aduertiſment of the ſtate thereof.</p>
            <p>There is built a fayer houſe capable well-nigh of a 100 perſons, for habitation of the ſtudents, and it proueth ſo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20150:35"/>
commodious, pleaſant, and healthful that none haue dyed ſince it was finiſhed, and verie few falne ſick, in ſo much as the laſt yeare whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there dyed in this citie a boue 6000. perſons of the plage, only one ſcholer of this Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary well ſicke of that deſeaſe, who yet recouered: ſo as it was atributed to Gods ſpeciall prouidence and protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who as it ſeemed had marked the walles of this colledge with the bloud of the holy martyrs of Ingland, that the angell of reuenge ſhould not touch the ſtudents. They liue ſo merily &amp; contentedly as them ſelues affirme they neuer liued with ſuch harty contentment in there owne fathers houſes. The grace which God giueth them, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the glorious vocation whereunto he calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue reddy to die for the conuerſion of there countrie, and the dayly vſe of prayer and other exerciſes of piety which they haue, kept them continually with feruour &amp; deuotion, notwithſtanding the diſtraction of theire ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, as wel appeared (to omitt other exampls) in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordenarie preparation they made, and the recollection this laſt ſommer in meditation &amp; prayer for many dayes together, to diſpoſe them ſelues to receiue worthely the lubely of the holy yeare, which was graunted by eſpeciall priuilege to the Ingliſh Catholikes, and in other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of late, wherein they haue made notable demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of theire religion and pietie eſpecially in the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and receiuing a deuout image of our bleſſed Lady de faced by the Ingliſh heretikes at Cadyz which no doubt, but God allmightie hath beſtowed vpon them in reward of theire ſpeciall loue and deuotion to his bleſſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is not a litle ſtirred vp and increaſed in this citie by theire example. They profit notably in all kynde of ſtudyes, ſpecially in philoſophy, diuinitie, and controuerſes againſt hereſes, wherein they defend their concluſions and publique acts with ſo great ſatisfaction and approbation of the whole vniuerſitie, as they are lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and eſteemed not only in this citie, but of the graue and learned perſons of al theſe kingdomes, ecleſiaſticall,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20150:35"/>
and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, and diuers of them haue adopted ſome one, ſome moe of theſe ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for their childeren, prouiding them of maintenance and apparrel, &amp; comforting them with gifts and lettrrs, and viſiting them in perſon as they were theire owne children, and the Biſhops when they take holy orders, and whole cities in occaſions ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king demonſtration of theire good wil and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, in ſo much, as theſe two yeares paſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable for general famin, and plage, when many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munities that enioy great liuings &amp; rents, found them ſelues ouercharged, this Colledge maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 60. or 70. perſons without want of any thing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, through Gods holy prouidence, who hath care in ſuch occaſions to ſuſteine at his owne expenſes thoſe that leaue theire parents and countrie for his holy name, as at other times he hath done with Daniel, Elias, S. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, and many other of his ſeruantes. Finally this good wil and eſtimation is ſo much the more to be accounted, of, as it is more vniuerſal and procedeth from perſons of more iudgment and authoritie, in which kinde, may be rekned the extraordinarie demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fauour which the high counſayles of theſe kingdomes haue ſhewed of late to this Ingliſh Colledge moued thereunto by the Earle of Ponion roſtro, don Franciſco Arias de Bouadilla who hauing bin Coronel in Flandres many yeares, and ſeeing the rigorous perſecution in Ingland and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of the Catholikes, and after knowne the Ingliſh Colledge of Ciuil, the time hee was gouerner of that citie, hath taken ſuch affection to this Colledge, that he dealeth in their buſineſſe with no leſſe care then if they were his owne childeren, and ſo vpon occaſion of two &amp; twentie ſtudents that came this yeare almoſt altogether, he preſented petitions to the Counſayles in his owne name, &amp; with al gaue them bookes of the hiſtorie new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed by the late kinges Confeſſor of the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Ingland, and a paper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayning diuers reaſons to moue affection towards theſe Seminaries, which he
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20150:36"/>
cauſed to bee printed for the purpoſe, and is worthy to be ſet, (as it ſhal be) downe at the end of his relation, as wel for teſtimonie of this good noblemans zeale &amp; affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as for your highneſſe, who cannot choſe to receiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, ſeeing layd together, and wel declared the grounds and foundation of the fauours, which your ſelf and the moſt renowmed kings, your father, &amp; your brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her, haue ſhewed in ſucouring this people that ſo much deſerueth to be ſucoured, &amp; the ſame is no ſmal teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the paſſion and blindneſſe which hereſie hath bred in thoſe of England, which perſecute euen to death theſe innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lambes of their owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey &amp; bloud, who one the other ſide, ſtrangers of a different nation are forced (only for the example of their good life &amp; vertue) to loue ſo tenderly &amp; with ſo general approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as may bee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in the fauours &amp; benefits which dayly they receiue of theire Maieſties, and your highneſſe, and ſo many other principal perſons of theſe kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; now lately of theſe counſayles and communities which is the greateſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie that can be of the general affection that is borne them. For notwithſtanding the fauour and affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which any Prince or Prelate ſheweth to a worke of this qualitie doth much commend and authoriſe it, yet many times it may proceed of a particular deuotion, &amp; therefore is not ſo great a teſtimony, nor ſo vniuerſal as his other approba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, but that ſo many counſayls as haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curred of late to fauour this worke &amp; ſo many perſons of authoritie as be in them, in whoſe wiſdome and diſcretion reſteth the gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſo many kingdomes &amp; countries, &amp; which do not eaſylie concurre in the qualification &amp; approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any thing, wherein may be doubt, ſhould ſo vnite and conioyne them ſelues in one mind and affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only to approue, but to fauour &amp; ſuccor an other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in a thing vnaccuſtomed &amp; hetherto not ſeene in any other occaſion, &amp; where only one negatiue voyce had bin ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to hinder the graunt, this I cannot ſee how any man can doubt to be his diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; handy worke, by whom
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20150:36"/>
               <hi>Reges regnant &amp; legum conditores iuſta decernunt,</hi> Kings do reigne and lawgiuers make iuſt decrees, therby to giue euident teſtimonie to the world, that he wil make fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and ennoble this his worke, to the greater confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the heretiks his enemyes who ſeek by al meanes poſſible to calumniat, ouerthrow, and deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>VVherefore there is no reaſon that thoſe whom God moſt merifully calleth to this holy worke, no leſſe hard then glorious, ſhould be diſmayed, or loſe hart with the troubles and new difficulties, which ariſe in it euery day, by the ſubtile meanes of the enemie of truth, ſeing his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie one the other ſyde hath ſuch particular care to prouide diligent workmen and labors for this his beloued vineyard whoſe learning confoundeth the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their enemies, there valor and vertue, the others malice, and there magnanimitie and patience, the others cruelty, vpholding and mayntaining by theſe meanes, the Catholike faith agaynſt al the power of the Prince of darknes. If then God hath effectuated the conuerſion of other countries, and of England alſo, at other times by only one, or two, or by ſome ſmal number of good men, what may wee hope for now of ſo many faithful ſeruants and workemen of his, as be in that countrie; and of the prouident care which (as wee ſee) he hath to cal ſo many choſen youth as euery day with ſingular &amp; ſtrange vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations come as a new ſupply to the Seminaries, where being brought vp trayned and exerciſed in vertue &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (the armes where with they muſt fight againſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) they become as valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Capitaines in this ſpiritual war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Church, as were Cyrus, Hannibal, Alexander, Auguſtus Caeſar, and Dauid in theire temporal warres, for that they began to exerciſe themſelues in them betimes (as their hiſtories reporte) what may wee then hope for, but a ſhort and happie end of this combate ſithence they go to it, with the ſkil, courage, and fortitude that beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſoldiours of Chriſt, as there imperiſonment, theire diſputations with the heretikes, theire torments, &amp;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20150:37"/>
deathes do teſtifie; ſo as iuſtly wee may ſay, that theſe be of the number of the wiſe childeren, which (as the holy ghoſt ſayeth) bring ioy and comfort to theire parents, &amp; not only comfort, but honour to them, and libertie to there country, and as God choſe the baniſhed chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren of Babylon, for inſtrumentes to worke and ſhew forth his glory, who rather choſe to enter into the hot burning fornace, in teſtimonie of there true religion, then to adore the idol; where by the king came to know his error, and acknowledged the true God: ſo by the very ſame meanes God is glorified with the conſtancie of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Ingliſh youthes, who break through ſo many dangers and perils, becauſe they wil not adore and follow the Idol of hereſie erected in their country but rather labour to reduce it to the knowledge and obedience of the true Catholike Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <head>The reaſons and motiues which the Earle of Ponion Roſtro, Don Franciſco Arias de Bouadilla, of the Kinges Councel, general gaue to the counſail of the inquiſition, to the counſail Real of Caſtilla, to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes of Italy, the Indies, and the crowne of Aragon, and to the Iunta de Cortes de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilla, which in Spaine is as the lower hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the parlament in Ingland, in behalfe of the Engliſh Seminary of Valladolid, in April 1600.</head>
            <p>IT appeareth ſufficiently how relgious and honorable a work the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Ingliſh ſeminaries in theſe kingdomes hath bin, &amp; how worthy they ar to be fauo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red as wel by the great priuileges which his holynes hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, as by the ſpecial fauours which our ſoueraine
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20150:37"/>
the Catholike king that now is, &amp; the glorious memory of his father haue done them, with more then heroical li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality &amp; piety, at the very times when by piracy &amp; ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inuaſions of other Ingliſhmen theire kingdomes, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects were moſt endamaged, declaring therewith the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this work, and that they had prudently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the important reaſons, why it ſhould be fauored.</p>
            <p>The ſame likewiſe may be confirmed by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Cardinal Baronius one of the greateſt &amp; moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned writers of this age who, ſpeaking of theſe ſeminaries, ſaith, that this age of ours is moſt fortunat in that it hath deſerued to bring forth ſo many holy preiſts crowned (as he ſaith) with more noble crownes of martirdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of S. Thomas of Canterbury ſeing they died not only with the ſame conſtancy for the defence of the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical liberty, as that renowmed martir did, but alſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue and reſtore the Catholique faith in theire cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, &amp; concludeth with theſe words, let my ſoule depart (ſaith he) in company of theſe iuſt and glorious champions.</p>
            <p>Botius alſo a learned and graue author in his booke of the markes of the trew Church of God recounteth theſe Ingliſh Seminaries for a moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimony &amp; proofe that our religion is founded in the truth, ſeing it indueth thoſe that profeſſe it with ſuch courage, and inuincible fortitude.</p>
            <p>Boterus an other author no leſſe graue and learned, commendeth this work, as one of the moſt glorious that hath bin in the church of God ſince the Apoſtles time.</p>
            <p>Laſtly the Biſhop of Tarazona that wrote the hiſtory of Ingland &amp; other prelats &amp; men of authority and great numbers of wiſe and learned men of theſe kingdomes, qualifie this worke for the moſt noble marke and blaſon in matter of faith &amp; religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that our kingdom of Spaine this day enioyeth.</p>
            <p>Although any one of theſe teſtimonies were ſufficient to declare the qualitie of this holy worke yet for that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny principal perſons haue ſo great eſtimation and deſire
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20150:38"/>
of the continuance and increaſe therof, as they perſwade themſelues the wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuffice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t notice to be the only cauſe why it is not generaly fauored and furthered of all I haue thought good to lay downe, certain particular reaſons &amp; motiues wher in is diſcouered the quality of the worke reducing them to three heades, the firſt of piety and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giou, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Chriſtian nobility and honor, and the third of commodity.</p>
            <div type="motives">
               <head>Motiues of piety.</head>
               <p>The firſt motiue and the moſt general is that to help theſe ſeminaries, is to ſuſtaine with temporal almes the faith of Chriſt &amp; the ſpiritual good of a kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſo dependeth of the labours and induſtry) of theſe Prieſts brought vp in theſe Seminaries that if they failed the vtter ruine and decay of Religion in that natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would follow. And therefore if it be an act of piety to repare the ruines of material temples, and ranſome any one Chriſtian from the captiuitie of infidels: it muſt needes be a far greater to build the Church of Chriſt, and redeeme from the tyranny of heretiks theſe vertuous young-men of whoſe ſafety dependeth the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo many ſoules in theire country, as after-ward by theire meanes ſhal come to know and imbrace the Catholike Religion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is that this kingdome which we ſuccour, was the firſt that in the whole world publiquely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the faith of Chriſt, and for this reſpect is called the firſt childe of the Church, and the dowry of our bleſſed lady, and in it flowriſhed afterwards the ſame faith for more then a 1000. yeares togeither, in which time it brought forth many holy kinges, Queenes, Biſhops, and other glorious ſaintes, and Martirs. And loſt not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of this faith ſo longe kept by any fault of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or corruption of manners and euil life as in other countries hath hapned, but by the miſerable fall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of King Henry the 8. and ſome of his children as to the world is euident, by the continual reſiſtance which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20150:38"/>
the Ingliſh Catholikes haue made ſo many yeares to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie neuer giuing it one houre of peaceable poſſeſſion though it haue coſt them theire bloud which they haue ſhed with ſo great conſtancy and courage, as highy edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth and aſtoniſheth the whole Church of God to ſee it.</p>
               <p>The third and more particular is, that the Catholikes for whoſe ſuccour and comfort theſe Prieſts are brought vp are on the one ſide the moſt afflicted with ſo long and rigorous a perſecution, and on the other the moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued with patience and longanimity, and the people to whome the profeſſion of theire religion coſteth more deare them to any other nation in the world.</p>
               <p>The fourth and not the leaſt is, the purity and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of life of theſe lawdable youngmen and the many tallents and graces wherewith God almighty enricheth them, and the account and eſtimation which they haue of the holy dignitie of preiſthood, for which many of them renounce their inheritance, &amp; which is more to be admired, after they be Prieſts notwithſtanding they know that many of theire companions ſent from the Seminaries, &amp; in particular from this of Valladolid, are at this preſent in priſon, and that others haue bin cruelly tormented, and others vnmercifully put to death by the heretiks, and that the diligence which they vſe in their purſute is incredible. Yet for all this they are not a whit diſmaid nor ſeeke occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſpend theire time in other countries more then is neceſſary to furniſh them ſelues with learning, but procure to haſten theire miſſion to England as much as in them lyeth departing after with ſo great alacrity courage, and comfort that they leaue theire companions and thoſe that ſend; them ful of admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration and holy deſirs to beare them company in theire glorious entrepriſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt reaſon is, that the end and inſtitution of theſe Seminaries is like vnto that which our Sauiour Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus purpoſed to him ſelfe, who (as himſelf declareth) prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipaly deſcended from heauen to recouer the loſt ſheepe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20150:39"/>
of the houſe of Iſrael his country where he was accuſed by the princes and elders of his owne people as a traytor and tumultuous perſon, that ſowed ſedition &amp; trobled the common wealth, and that according to their lawes was guilty of death. The ſame in proportion is the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and end of theſe Seminaries, and of the ſame cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes are the ſtudents and Preiſts wrongfully accuſed by the Ingliſh heretikes, who likewiſe haue made vniuſt lawes againſt them vnder colour whereof, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne them to death; &amp; laſtly, our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, impriſoned, diſgraced, crucified &amp; put to death in his owne country, and by his owne people, for hauing procurtd theire ſaluation, and for the like cauſes ar theſe Preiſts put in priſon, ſlandred, tormented, condemned, and put to death in Ingland, imitating that eminent and ſupreme degree of charity to the which S. Iohn exhorteth vs, <hi>Quoniam ille animam ſuam poſuit pro nobis &amp; nos debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus pro fratribus animas ponere</hi> that as Chriſt offred his life for our ſaluation: ſo ſhould wee according to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſpend freely our bloud to ſaue our bretheren.</p>
               <p>The ſixt is the great conſolation which theſe Prieſts receiue at theire returne to Ingland, when they finde many of theire ſchoolefellowes and equales brought vp and infected with hereſie only for want of the benefit of theſe Seminaries, which they haue enioyed, whereby of force muſt increaſe in them affects of gratitude to theire benefactors, and theire care dubbled, to recommend them to almighty God, of whoſe names to this end they carry particular memory when they departe in their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, remaining their perpetual chaplaines during their liues, and if they dy in defence of the faith, theire bloud wil aſke reward for them that brought them vp with ſo greath charity, as the bloud of Abel cried vengance at Gods hands againſt his Brother Caine that violently ſhed it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="motives">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20150:39"/>
               <head>Motiues of honor and Chriſtian nobility.</head>
               <p>The firſt motiue is that this worke diſcouereth and commendeth greatly to all the world the true &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian nobilitie of Spaine, and of the Catholiques of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland whereof theſe Seminaries ſhal be perpetual witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to al ages following ſeeing the very walles of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge teſtifie to our poſterity, this new and ſtraing exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of piety &amp; religion, that being actual exerciſe of war be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe twoo nations, theſe of Ingland ſend their children with ſo great confidence and no leſſe peril and dainger to be brought vp in Spaine, and that heere they are receiued ſo louingly and intreated ſo honorably as if they were our owne children a thing ſo vnſual amongſt other nations in like caſes that neither the memories of men nor hiſtories record the like, and is an euident ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the great opinion which Ingland hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of the Heroycal ſincerity and Chriſtianity of Spaine, ſeing the heretikes feare vs ſo much and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes ſo confidently rely vpon vs in theire neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which if no other reſpect were, doeth oblige vs in honor to maintaine, conſerue, and increaſe this holy worke, and to commend to al eternity the glorious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory thereof.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that this fauour and ſuccour is done to perſons of good patentage (for ſuch they are that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily come to theſe Seminaries) who to conſerue theire faith haue left theire country, freindes, and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, &amp; in the flower of theire age, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others carle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly neglect theire ſaluation, labor not only to ſaue their owne but alſo otherme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſoules taking vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theire youth the ſame entrepriſe, which in riper yeares the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles vndertooke and others theire followers. which firſt planted the ſaith in theſe and other kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of Chriſtendome, and here in the Seminaries theſe bind them ſelues by ſolemne oth to reduce theire country to the Catholike Church or to looſe theire liues in the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20150:40"/>
action, which they accompliſh ſo faithfully that in theſe few yeares almoſt 200. Prieſts haue bin put to death for defence of this glorious quarel, and ſo their aduerſaries are more afraid of this ſpiritual war, then of any enimy how powerful ſo euer, and they haue reaſon, for here Chriſt is the Captaine, and the war is not againſt the bodyes, but againſt the vnderſtandinges and corrupted wils of the deceiued, and ſo as we ſee they go for-ward conquering, diſtroying, and making hauock of heteſy, and putting to flight the enemyes of truth which no way are able to reſiſt them, and the great ſolicitude and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary diligence wherewith theire followers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments procure to aprehended theſe Prieſts, ſeruing rather for a ſigne then for a remidy of theire feare, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth the infinite wiſdome of God, who with a few children wageth ſuch irreſiſtable war againſt the Princes and powers of darknes.</p>
               <p>The third is, that if it were great reputation and honor for vs &amp; our natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by force of armes to deliuer the realm of Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from hereſy, it wil be more honorable to reduce it to the catholck church by theſe other meanes of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſouldiours whome we bring vp for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The fourth is, that if heretikes for a vaine imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of infernal honor, ioyn handes; and ſuccour one an other as hath bin ſeene in the Hugonots of Fraunce, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes of Almany, &amp; the continual ſupply both of mony and men, which theſe of Ingland for many yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue ſent to the heretikes of Scotland, and Fraunce, &amp; to the rebels of Flanders, ſparing no coſt nor labor by which the wicked eſtate of hereſy might be vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is moſt iuſt that the kingdomes of Spain (which God hath bleſſed and renowmed aboue all other naions with purity and integrity of faith) ſhould haue far greater reſpect of this moſt Chriſtian honor, and eſteeme it more in procu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring to maintaine, healp, &amp; conſerue the Catholik faith where it is alreddy, or to reſtor it in thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries wher it hath periſhed, and ſpecially in Ingland, which hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred
<pb facs="tcp:20150:40"/>
with ſo great conſtancy, ſo long and grecuous a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for defence of theire faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="motives">
               <head>Motiues of temporal commodity.</head>
               <p>The infinit wiſedom of god hath ſo diſpoſed the affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of Spain, and knit them ſo together, with the proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges of Ingland that the tranquility, ſecurity, &amp; weale publick of the one wholy dependeth of the others co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for as long as hereſy ſhal beare ſway in Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo long wil continew the inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſperat &amp; dangerous practiſes wherewith they moleſt vs &amp; our countries, &amp; this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion it ſemeth God wil haue brought to paſſe by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes of preaching his holy goſpel, to the end, al the glory may be his, ſeing theſe Prieſts of the Seminaries haue ſo proſperous ſucceſſe and reaped ſo aboundant fruit in their miſſions with the example of theire patience and conſtancy in their priſons, torments, and death it ſelf, &amp; with theire zeale, care and diligence in the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy Sacraments, and propagation of the truth, of which plentiful harueſt, and continual increaſe of faith &amp; religion, wee need no other teſtimony, then the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcations and ſummes of mony which the Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſantes pay euery yeare to the Queene to be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> going to the heretical ſeruice, &amp; the many young gentle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men of not able talents which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinualy come to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, as ſparkles of fire that fly out of that fornace of faith, which God hath miraculouſly kindled in that king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, where ſo great a number of Preiſts ar allredy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and others enter of freſh euery day, and yet the Catholikes are not content but continualy cry out for more, in ſo much that if wee could ſend as many as they deſire and haue neede of, wee ſhould ſee in few yeares the conuerſion of that country, &amp; withal enioy the ſecurity and proſperity of theſe kingdomes, &amp; the reſt of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous that wee enioyed before the breach of Ingland which ioyned againe with vs in peace &amp; concord (which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20150:41"/>
wil neuer be durable without conformity of religion) we may expect the auncient trafick again and good correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence ſo profitable to both partes, as the want thereof theſe yeares paſt doeth declare, and to renew &amp; eſtabliſh againe this confederation and freindſhippe, there cannot be found any other agents or ſolicitours ſo fit as theſe Preiſts brought vp in the Seminaries, who as they cannot loſe the natural loue to theire country, ſo can they not but carry allwaies moſt tender and gratfull affection to that which nouriſhed and brought them vp in theire tender yeares, ſo as the fruit of theire labors infallibly wil be in fine the concluſion of true and ſtable peace, ſo much deſired of both parts, wherewith we ſhall poſſeſſe ſecurity in our coaſts, and excuſe the infinite charges ſpent euery yeare in the conuoy of our Indian fleetes. The rebels of Flandres wil be forced to yeild, ſeing that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſuccour of England they haue neither courage nor force to maintaine theire rebellion. The neceſſity and charges of Armados wil be ended, and finally the ſpiritual good of that kingdom would redowne both to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and temporal commmodity of this.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the reaſons and motiues which this good no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man ſet downe &amp; gaue to the Counſailes aboue ſaid in behalf of the Ingliſh Seminaries and thoſe which are brought vp in them, with ſo laudable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple as the world ſeeth, and partly may be gathered by theſe relations. And the memorie of theſe ſo good children muſt needes comfort and encorage (in theire abſence) ſo Catholike parents which not only ſuffer for theſame faith with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient empriſonment and loſſe of theire goods, but alſo depriue them ſelues of the ioy and comfort, which pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents receiue by the preſence and ſight of theire children for the glory of Chriſt, and good of theire country, the memory therefore, of ſo noble parents and children ſhal alwayes flowiſh in the Church, and giueth vs great hope that this longe and rigourous winter of theire perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhal ſoone haue an end, and a peaceable and pleaſant
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20150:41"/>
ſpring-time ariſe, and that after this dark night of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and ſinne that hath couered the auncient bewty and glory of that country, the bright Sunne of Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhal retourne againe: which our Lord Ieſu of his infinit mercy bring to ſpeedy effect. Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20150:42"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:20150:42"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:20150:43"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:20150:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
